<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ JBoss DNA (http://www.jboss.org/dna)
  ~
  ~ See the COPYRIGHT.txt file distributed with this work for information
  ~ regarding copyright ownership.  Some portions may be licensed
  ~ to Red Hat, Inc. under one or more contributor license agreements.
  ~ See the AUTHORS.txt file in the distribution for a full listing of 
  ~ individual contributors.
  ~
  ~ JBoss DNA is free software. Unless otherwise indicated, all code in JBoss DNA
  ~ is licensed to you under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as
  ~ published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of
  ~ the License, or (at your option) any later version.
  ~
  ~ JBoss DNA is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY
  ~ or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ for more details.
  ~
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ along with this distribution; if not, write to:
  ~ Free Software Foundation, Inc.
  ~ 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor
  ~ Boston, MA  02110-1301  USA
  -->
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"	[
<!ENTITY % CustomDTD SYSTEM "../custom.dtd">
%CustomDTD;
]>
<chapter id="configuration">
  <title>Configuring and Using JBoss DNA</title>
	<para>Using JBoss DNA within your application is actually quite straightforward.  As you'll see in this chapter,
		the first step is setting up JBoss DNA and starting the <code>JcrEngine</code>.  After that, you obtain the
		<code>javax.jcr.Repository</code> instance for a named repository and just use the standard JCR API throughout your
		application.
	</para>
	<sect1 id="jcr_engine">
		<title>JBoss DNA's JcrEngine</title>
		<para>
			JBoss DNA encapsulates everything necessary to run one or more JCR repositories into a single &JcrEngine; instance.
			This includes all underlying repository sources, the pools of connections to the sources, the sequencers,
			the MIME type detector(s), and the &Repository; implementations.
		</para>
		<para>
			Obtaining a &JcrEngine; instance is very easy - assuming that you have a valid &JcrConfiguration; instance.  We'll see
			how to get one of those in a little bit, but if you have one then all you have to do is build and start the engine:
		</para>
    <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[
JcrConfiguration config = ...
JcrEngine engine = config.build();
engine.start();
 ]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			Obtaining a JCR &Repository; instance is a matter of simply asking the engine for it by the name defined in the configuration:
		</para>
    <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[
javax.jcr.Repository repository = engine.getRepository("Name of repository");
 ]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			At this point, your application can proceed by working with the JCR API.
		</para>
		<para>
			And, once you're finished with the &JcrEngine;, you should shut it down:
		</para>
    <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[
engine.shutdown();
engine.awaitTermination(3,TimeUnit.SECONDS);	// optional
 ]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			When the <code>shutdown()</code> method is called, the &Repository; instances managed by the engine are marked as being shut down,
			and they will not be able to create new &Session;s.  However, any existing &Session;s or ongoing operations (e.g., event notifications)
			present at the time of the <code>shutdown()</code> call will be allowed to finish.  
			In essence, <code>shutdown()</code> is a <emphasis>graceful</emphasis> request, and since it may take some time to complete,
			you can wait until the shutdown has completed by simply calling <code>awaitTermination(...)</code> as shown above.
			This method will block until the engine has indeed shutdown or until the supplied time duration has passed (whichever comes first).
			And, yes, you can call the <code>awaitTermination(...)</code> method repeatedly if needed.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="jcr_configuration">
		<title>JcrConfiguration</title>
		<para>
			The previous section assumed the existence of a &JcrConfiguration;.  It's not really that creating an instance is all that difficult.
			In fact, there's only one no-argument constructor, so actually creating the instance is a piece of cake.  What can be a little more challenging,
			though, is setting up the &JcrConfiguration; instance, which must define the following components:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="strong"><code>Repository sources</code></emphasis> are the POJO objects that each describe a particular
					location where content is stored.  Each repository source object is an instance of a JBoss DNA connector, and is configured
					with the properties that particular source.  JBoss DNA's &RepositorySource; classes are analogous to JDBC's &DataSource; classes -
					they are implemented by specific connectors (aka, "drivers") for specific kinds of repository sources (aka, "databases").
					Similarly, a &RepositorySource; instance is analogous to a &DataSource; instance, with bean properties for each configurable
					parameter.  Therefore, each repository source definition must supply the name of the &RepositorySource; class, any
					bean properties, and, optionally, the classpath that should be used to load the class. </para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="strong"><code>Repositories</code></emphasis> define the JCR repositories that are available.  Each
					repository has a unique name that is used to obtain the &Repository; instance from the &JcrEngine;'s <code>getRepository(String)</code>
					method, but each repository definition also can include the predefined namespaces (other than those automatically defined by
					JBoss DNA), various options, and the node types that are to be available in the repository without explicit registration
					through the JCR API.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="strong"><code>Sequencers</code></emphasis> define the particular sequencers that are available for use.
					Each sequencer definition provides the path expressions governing which nodes in the repository should be sequenced when those nodes change,
					and where the resulting output generated by the sequencer should be placed.  The definition also must state the name of 
					the sequencer class, any bean properties and, optionally, the classpath that should be used to load the class.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="strong"><code>MIME type detectors</code></emphasis> define the particular MIME type detector(s) that should
					be made available.  A MIME type detector does exactly what the name implies: it attempts to determine the MIME type given a
					"filename" and contents.  JBoss DNA automatically uses a detector that uses the file extension to identify the MIME type,
					but also provides an implementation that uses an external library to identify the MIME type based upon the contents.
					The definition must state the name of the detector class, any bean properties and, optionally, the classpath that should 
					be used to load the class.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			There really are three options:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="strong"><code>Load from a file</code></emphasis> is conceptually the easiest and requires the least amount
					of Java code, but it now requires a configuration file.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="strong"><code>Load from a configuration repository</code></emphasis> is not much more complicated than loading
					from a file, but it does allow multiple &JcrEngine; instances (usually in different processes perhaps on different machines)
					to easily access their (shared) configuration.  And technically, loading the configuration from a file really just creates an
					&InMemoryRepositorySource;, imports the configuration file into that source, and then proceeds with this approach.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="strong"><code>Programmatic configuration</code></emphasis> is always possible, even if the configuration is loaded
					from a file or repository.  Using the &JcrConfiguration;'s API, you can define (or update or remove) all of the definitions that make
					up a configuration.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
			Each of these approaches has their obvious advantages, so the choice of which one to use is entirely up to you.
		</para>
		<sect2 id="loading_from_file">
			<title>Loading from a configuration file</title>
			<para>
				Loading the JBoss DNA configuration from a file is actually very simple:
			</para>
    	<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[
JcrConfiguration config = new JcrConfiguration();
configuration.loadFrom(file);
 ]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				where the <code>file</code> parameter can actually be a &File; instance, a &URL; to the file, an &InputStream; 
				containing the contents of the file, or even a &String; containing the contents of the file.  
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>The <code>loadFrom(...)</code> method can be called any number of times, but each time it is called it completely wipes
				  out any current notion of the configuration and replaces it with the configuration found in the file.
				</para>
			</note>
			<para>
				There is an optional second parameter that defines the &Path; within the configuration file identifying the parent node of the various
				configuration nodes.  If not specified, it assumes "/".  This makes it possible for the configuration content to be
				located at a different location in the hierarchical structure.  (This is not often required, but when it is required
				this second parameter is very useful.)
			</para>
			<para>
				Here is the configuration file that is used in the repository example, though it has been simplified a bit and most comments 
				have been removed for clarity):
			</para>
    	<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration xmlns="http://www.jboss.org/dna/1.0" xmlns:jcr="http://www.jcp.org/jcr/1.0">
	  <!-- 
	  Define the JCR repositories 
	  -->
	  <dna:repositories>
	      <!-- 
	      Define a JCR repository that accesses the 'Cars' source directly.
	      This of course is optional, since we could access the same content through 'vehicles'.
	      -->
	      <dna:repository jcr:name="car repository" dna:source="Cars">
	          <options jcr:primaryType="dna:options"/>
	              <jaasLoginConfigName jcr:primaryType="dna:option" dna:value="dna-jcr"/>
	          </options>
	      </dna:repository>
	  </dna:repositories>
    <!-- 
    Define the sources for the content.  These sources are directly accessible using the DNA-specific Graph API.
    -->
    <dna:sources jcr:primaryType="nt:unstructured">
        <dna:source jcr:name="Cars" dna:classname="org.jboss.dna.graph.connector.inmemory.InMemoryRepositorySource" dna:retryLimit="3" dna:defaultWorkspaceName="workspace1"/>
        <dna:source jcr:name="Aircraft" dna:classname="org.jboss.dna.graph.connector.inmemory.InMemoryRepositorySource">
            <!-- Define the name of the workspace used by default.  Optional, but convenient. -->
            <defaultWorkspaceName>workspace2</defaultWorkspaceName>
        </dna:source>
    </dna:sources>
    <!-- 
    Define the sequencers. This is an optional section. For this example, we're not using any sequencers. 
    -->
    <dna:sequencers>
        <!--dna:sequencer jcr:name="Image Sequencer" dna:classname="org.jboss.dna.sequencer.image.ImageMetadataSequencer">
            <dna:description>Image metadata sequencer</dna:description>        
            <dna:pathExpression>/foo/source => /foo/target</dna:pathExpression>
            <dna:pathExpression>/bar/source => /bar/target</dna:pathExpression>
        </dna:sequencer-->
    </dna:sequencers>
    <dna:mimeTypeDetectors>
        <dna:mimeTypeDetector jcr:name="Detector" dna:description="Standard extension-based MIME type detector"/>
    </dna:mimeTypeDetectors>
</configuration>
 ]]></programlisting>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="loading_from_repository">
			<title>Loading from a configuration repository</title>
			<para>
				Loading the JBoss DNA configuration from an existing repository is also pretty straightforward.  Simply create and configure the
				&RepositorySource; instance to point to the desired repository, and then call the <code>loadFrom(&RepositorySource; source)</code>
				method:
			</para>
    	<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[
RepositorySource configSource = ...
JcrConfiguration config = new JcrConfiguration();
configuration.loadFrom(configSource);
 ]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				This really is a more advanced way to define your configuration, so we won't go into how you configure a &RepositorySource;.
				For more information, consult the &ReferenceGuide;.
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>The <code>loadFrom(...)</code> method can be called any number of times, but each time it is called it completely wipes
				  out any current notion of the configuration and replaces it with the configuration found in the file.
				</para>
			</note>
			<para>
				There is an optional second parameter that defines the name of the workspace in the supplied source where the configuration content
				can be found.  It is not needed if the workspace is the source's default workspace. 
				There is an optional third parameter that defines the &Path; within the configuration repository identifying the parent node of the various
				configuration nodes.  If not specified, it assumes "/".  This makes it possible for the configuration content to be
				located at a different location in the hierarchical structure.  (This is not often required, but when it is required
				this second parameter is very useful.)
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="programmatic_configuration">
			<title>Programmatic configuration</title>
			<para>
				Defining the configuration programmatically is not terribly complicated, and it for obvious reasons results in more verbose Java code.
				But this approach is very useful and often the easiest approach when the configuration must change or is a reflection of other
				dynamic information.
			</para>
			<para>
				The &JcrConfiguration; class was designed to have an easy-to-use API that makes it easy to configure each of the different kinds of
				components, especially when using an IDE with code completion.  Here are several examples:
			</para>
			<sect3 id="programmatically_configuring_sources">
				<title>Repository sources</title>
				<para>Each repository source definition must include the name of the &RepositorySource; class as well as each bean property
					that should be set on the object:
				</para>
    		<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[
JcrConfiguration config = ...
config.repositorySource("source A")
      .usingClass(InMemoryRepositorySource.class)
      .setDescription("The repository for our content")
      .setProperty("defaultWorkspaceName", workspaceName);
 ]]></programlisting>
				<para>
					This example defines an in-memory source with the name "source A", a description, and a single "defaultWorkspaceName" bean property.
					Different &RepositorySource; implementations will the bean properties that are required and optional.
					Of course, the class can be specified as Class reference or a string (followed by whether the class should be loaded from
					the classpath or from a specific classpath).
				</para>
				<note>
					<para>Each time <code>repositorySource(String)</code> is called, it will either load the existing definition with the supplied
					name or will create a new definition if one does not already exist.  To remove a definition, simply call <code>remove()</code>
					on the result of <code>repositorySource(String)</code>.
					The set of existing definitions can be accessed with the <code>repositorySources()</code> method.
					</para>
				</note>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="programmatically_configuring_repositories">
				<title>Repositories</title>
				<para>Each repository must be defined to use a named repository source, but all other aspects (e.g., namespaces, node types, options) 
					are optional.</para> 
    		<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[
JcrConfiguration config = ...
config.repository("repository A")
      .addNodeTypes("myCustomNodeTypes.cnd")
      .setSource("source 1")
      .registerNamespace("acme","http://www.example.com/acme")
      .setOption(JcrRepository.Option.JAAS_LOGIN_CONFIG_NAME, "dna-jcr");
 ]]></programlisting>
				<para>
					This example defines a repository that uses the "source 1" repository source (which could be a federated source, an in-memory source,
					a database store, or any other source).  Additionally, this example adds the node types in the "myCustomNodeTypes.cnd" file as those
					that will be made available when the repository is accessed.  It also defines the "http://www.example.com/acme" namespace,
					and finally sets the "JAAS_LOGIN_CONFIG_NAME" option to define the name	of the JAAS login configuration that should be used by 
					the JBoss DNA repository.
				</para>
				<note>
					<para>Each time <code>repository(String)</code> is called, it will either load the existing definition with the supplied
					name or will create a new definition if one does not already exist.  To remove a definition, simply call <code>remove()</code>
					on the result of <code>repository(String)</code>.
					The set of existing definitions can be accessed with the <code>repositories()</code> method.
					</para>
				</note>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="programmatically_configuring_sequencers">
				<title>Sequencers</title>
				<para>Each defined sequencer must specify the name of the &StreamSequencer; implementation class as well as the path expressions
					defining which nodes should be sequenced and the output paths defining where the sequencer output should be placed (often as a function
					of the input path expression).</para> 
    		<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[
JcrConfiguration config = ...
config.sequencer("Image Sequencer")
      .usingClass("org.jboss.dna.sequencer.image.ImageMetadataSequencer")
      .loadedFromClasspath()
      .setDescription("Sequences image files to extract the characteristics of the image")
      .sequencingFrom("//(*.(jpg|jpeg|gif|bmp|pcx|png|iff|ras|pbm|pgm|ppm|psd)[*])/jcr:content[@jcr:data]")
      .andOutputtingTo("/images/$1");
 ]]></programlisting>
				<para>
					This shows an example of a sequencer definition named "Image Sequencer" that uses the &ImageMetadataSequencer; class 
					(loaded from the classpath), that is to sequence the "jcr:data" property on any new or changed nodes that are named 
					"jcr:content" below a parent node	with a name ending in ".jpg", ".jpeg", ".gif", ".bmp", ".pcx", ".iff", ".ras", 
					".pbm", ".pgm", ".ppm" or ".psd".  The output of the sequencing operation should be placed at the "/images/$1" node,
					where the "$1" value is captured as the name of the parent node.  (The capture groups work the same was as regular expressions;
					see the &ReferenceGuide; for more details.)
					Of course, the class can be specified as Class reference or a string (followed by whether the class should be loaded from
					the classpath or from a specific classpath).
				</para>
				<note>
					<para>Each time <code>sequencer(String)</code> is called, it will either load the existing definition with the supplied
					name or will create a new definition if one does not already exist.  To remove a definition, simply call <code>remove()</code>
					on the result of <code>sequencer(String)</code>.
					The set of existing definitions can be accessed with the <code>sequencers()</code> method.
					</para>
				</note>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="programmatically_configuring_mime_type_detectors">
				<title>MIME type detectors</title>
				<para>Each defined MIME type detector must specify the name of the &MimeTypeDetector; implementation class as well as any
					other bean properties required by the implementation.</para> 
    		<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[
JcrConfiguration config = ...
config.mimeTypeDetector("Extension Detector")
      .usingClass(org.jboss.dna.graph.mimetype.ExtensionBasedMimeTypeDetector.class);
 ]]></programlisting>
				<para>
					Of course, the class can be specified as Class reference or a string (followed by whether the class should be loaded from
					the classpath or from a specific classpath).
				</para>
				<note>
					<para>Each time <code>mimeTypeDetector(String)</code> is called, it will either load the existing definition with the supplied
					name or will create a new definition if one does not already exist.  To remove a definition, simply call <code>remove()</code>
					on the result of <code>mimeTypeDetector(String)</code>.  
					The set of existing definitions can be accessed with the <code>mimeTypeDetectors()</code> method.
					</para>
				</note>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="using_dna_whats_next">
		<title>What's next</title>
		<para>
			This chapter outline how you configure JBoss DNA, how you then access a <code>javax.jcr.Repository</code> instance,
			and use the standard JCR API to interact with the repository. The
			<link linkend="downloading_and_running">next chapter </link> walks you through downloading
			and running the JBoss DNA examples. 
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
