<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ JBoss DNA (http://www.jboss.org/dna)
  ~
  ~ See the COPYRIGHT.txt file distributed with this work for information
  ~ regarding copyright ownership.  Some portions may be licensed
  ~ to Red Hat, Inc. under one or more contributor license agreements.
  ~ See the AUTHORS.txt file in the distribution for a full listing of 
  ~ individual contributors.
  ~
  ~ JBoss DNA is free software. Unless otherwise indicated, all code in JBoss DNA
  ~ is licensed to you under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as
  ~ published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of
  ~ the License, or (at your option) any later version.
  ~
  ~ JBoss DNA is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY
  ~ or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ for more details.
  ~
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ along with this distribution; if not, write to:
  ~ Free Software Foundation, Inc.
  ~ 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor
  ~ Boston, MA  02110-1301  USA
  -->
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"	[
<!ENTITY % CustomDTD SYSTEM "../custom.dtd">
%CustomDTD;
]>
<chapter id="environment">
  <title>Environment</title>
  <para>
		The various components of JBoss DNA are designed as plain old Java objects, or POJOs.  And rather than making assumptions
		about their environment, each component instead requires that any external dependencies necessary for it to operate
		must be supplied to it.  This pattern is known as Dependency Injection, and it allows the components to be simpler
		and allows for a great deal of flexibility and customization in how the components are configured.  
		And, JBoss DNA will soon provide a higher-level component that leverages the 
		<ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/jbossmc">JBoss Microcontainer</ulink> to automatically assemble and wire together
		all the lower-level components.
  </para>
	<sect1 id="security">
		<title>Security</title>
	  <para>
	    JBoss DNA uses the
	    <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/javase/technologies/security/">Java Authentication and Authorization Service (JAAS)</ulink>
	    for its security mechanism. Not only is this the standard approach for authenticating and authorizing in Java, but
			it also enables JBoss DNA to integrate existing security systems.  
	  </para>
	  <para>
			There are quite a few JAAS providers available, but one of the best and most powerful providers is
	    <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/jbosssecurity/">JBoss Security</ulink>, which is the open source
			security framework used by JBoss.  JBoss Security offers a number of JAAS login modules, including:
	    <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>
	          <emphasis role="strong">User-Roles Login Module</emphasis>
	          is a simple
	          <code>javax.security.auth.login.LoginContext</code>
	          implementation that uses usernames and passwords stored in a properties file.
	        </para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>
	          <emphasis role="strong">Client Login Module</emphasis>
	          prompts the user for their username and password.
	        </para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>
	          <emphasis role="strong">Database Server Login Module</emphasis>
	          uses a JDBC database to authenticate principals and associate them with roles.
	        </para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>
	          <emphasis role="strong">LDAP Login Module</emphasis>
	          uses an LDAP directory to authenticate principals. Two implementations are available.
	        </para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>
	          <emphasis role="strong">Certificate Login Module</emphasis>
	          authenticates using X509 certificates, obtaining roles from either property files or a JDBC database.
	        </para>
	      </listitem>
	      <listitem>
	        <para>
	          <emphasis role="strong">Operating System Login Module</emphasis>
	          authenticates using the operating system's mechanism.
	        </para>
	      </listitem>
	    </itemizedlist>
	    and many others.  Plus, JBoss Security also provides other capabilities, such as using XACML policies or using federated single sign-on. 
			For more detail, see the <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/jbosssecurity/">JBoss Security</ulink> project.
	  </para>
		<sect2 id="authentication">
			<title>Authenticating with JAAS</title>
			<para>
				JBoss DNA defers to JAAS to authenticate clients creating repository connections (known as JCR Sessions if using the JCR API),
				and generally expects the client application to obtain the JAAS &LoginContext; or &AppControlContext;.
				These are then passed to JBoss DNA, which merely verifies that authentication has been done.
			</para>
			<para>
				As we'll see in the <link linkend="execution-context">next section</link>, JBoss DNA has the notion of an &ExecutionContext;
				that can be created using JAAS login or access control contexts.  These execution contexts therefore contain information
				about the subject.
			</para>
			<para>
				We'll also see in the <link linkend="jcr">chapter on JCR</link> how JAAS can be used for authentication when
				JCR Sessions are created.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="authorization">
			<title>Authorization with JAAS</title>
			<para>
				JBoss DNA does not currently use any of the authorization features of JAAS.  However, in future releases where authorization
				is supported, JBoss DNA will rely upon JAAS authorization just as it currently does for authentication.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="execution-context">
		<title>Execution contexts</title>
		<para>
			One of the objects that must be supplied to many JBoss DNA components is an &ExecutionContext;.  Some components 
			require this context to be passed into individual methods, allowing the context to vary with each method invocation.
			Other components require the context to be provided before it's used, and will use that context for all its operations
			(until it is given a different one).
		</para>
		<para>
			What does an &ExecutionContext; represent?  Quite simply, it's the set of objects that define the environment
			or context in which the method or component is currently operating.  It includes a way for recording and reporting 
			errors and problems.  It includes the ability to <link linkend="classloaders">create class loaders</link> 
			given a classpath of class loader names. It also includes information about the current <link linkend="security">user</link>.
			It includes access to factories that can be used to create and convert property values. And it includes factories 
			for working with namespaces and fully-qualified names.  In fact, as JBoss DNA evolves, more things may need to be
			added.  Here is what the &ExecutionContext; interface looks like:
		</para>
	  <programlisting>
public class &ExecutionContext; implements &ClassLoaderFactory; {

    /**
     * Get the factories that should be used to create values for {@link Property properties}.
     * @return the property value factory; never null
     */
    public &ValueFactories; getValueFactories() {...}

    /**
     * Get the namespace registry for this context.
     * @return the namespace registry; never null
     */
    public &NamespaceRegistry; getNamespaceRegistry() {...}

    /**
     * Get the factory for creating {@link Property} objects.
     * @return the property factory; never null
     */
    public &PropertyFactory; getPropertyFactory() {...}

    /**
     * Get the current JAAS access control context.
     * @return the access control context; may be <code>null</code>
     */
    public &AccessControlContext; getAccessControlContext() {...}

    /**
     * Get the current JAAS login context.
     * @return the login context; may be <code>null</code>
     */
    public &LoginContext; getLoginContext() {...}

    /**
     * Get the JAAS subject for which this context was created.
     * @return the subject; never null
     */
    public &Subject; getSubject() {...}

    /**
     * Return a logger associated with this context. This logger records only those activities within the 
     * context and provide a way to capture the context-specific activities. All log messages are also
     * sent to the system logger, so classes that log via this mechanism should <i>not</i> also 
     * {@link Logger#getLogger(Class) obtain a system logger}.
     * @param clazz the class that is doing the logging
     * @return the logger, named after <code>clazz</code>; never null
     */
    public &Logger; getLogger( Class&lt;?> clazz ) {...}

    /**
    * Return a logger associated with this context. This logger records only those activities within the 
    * context and provide a way to capture the context-specific activities. All log messages are also
    * sent to the system logger, so classes that log via this mechanism should <i>not</i> also 
    * {@link Logger#getLogger(Class) obtain a system logger}.
     * @param name the name for the logger
     * @return the logger, named after <code>clazz</code>; never null
     */
    public &Logger; getLogger( String name ) {...}

		...
}
</programlisting>
		<para>
			Notice that &ExecutionContext; implements the &ClassLoaderFactory; interface described in the
			<link linkend="classloaders">previous chapter</link>, meaning it can be used to create other contexts.  These other methods are not shown,
			but can be used to create create subcontexts with different <link linkend="security">JAAS</link>
			login or access control contexts, with different namespace registry, or with different combinations of components.
		</para>
	  <para>
			The fact that so many of the JBoss DNA components take &ExecutionContext; instances gives us some interesting possibilities.  
			For example, one execution context instance can be used as the highest-level (or "application-level") context for all of the services 
			(e.g., &RepositoryService;, &SequencingService;, etc.).
			Then, an execution context could be created for each user that will be performing operations, and that user's context can
			be passed around to not only provide security information about the user but also to allow the activities being performed
			to be recorded for user feedback, monitoring and/or auditing purposes.
		</para>
		<para>
			The following code fragment shows how easy it is to create various execution contexts:
		</para>
	  <programlisting>
&ExecutionContext; context1 = new &ExecutionContext;();

// Create a context for a user, authenticating using JAAS ...
&LoginContext; loginContext = new LoginContext("username",callbackHandler);
&ExecutionContext; context2 = context1.with(new LoginContext("username"));

// Create a context for the same user, authenticating using JAAS, and using a different callback handler ...
&CallbackHandler; callbackHandler = ...
&LoginContext; loginContext = new LoginContext("username",callbackHandler);
&ExecutionContext; context3 = context1.with(loginContext);
</programlisting>
		<para>
			These contexts can then be passed to the various components as needed.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<para>
			In this chapter, we covered security and environment topics as used throughout JBoss DNA. 
			The <link linkend="repositories">next chapter</link> will cover JBoss DNA repositories, including the connector framework,
			how DNA's JCR implementation works with connectors, what connectors are available (and how to use them),
			and how to write your own connector.
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>

