<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ ModeShape (http://www.modeshape.org)
  ~
  ~ See the COPYRIGHT.txt file distributed with this work for information
  ~ regarding copyright ownership.  Some portions may be licensed
  ~ to Red Hat, Inc. under one or more contributor license agreements.
  ~ See the AUTHORS.txt file in the distribution for a full listing of 
  ~ individual contributors.
  ~
  ~ ModeShape is free software. Unless otherwise indicated, all code in ModeShape
  ~ is licensed to you under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as
  ~ published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of
  ~ the License, or (at your option) any later version.
  ~
  ~ ModeShape is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY
  ~ or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ for more details.
  ~
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ along with this distribution; if not, write to:
  ~ Free Software Foundation, Inc.
  ~ 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor
  ~ Boston, MA  02110-1301  USA
  -->
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"	[
<!ENTITY % CustomDTD SYSTEM "../../custom.dtd">
%CustomDTD;
]>
<chapter id="jdbc-storage-connector">
  <title>JPA Connector</title>
  <para>
		This connector stores a graph of any structure or size in a relational database, using a JPA provider on top of a JDBC driver. 
		Currently this connector relies upon some Hibernate-specific capabilities.  The schema of the database is dictated by this
		connector and is optimized for storing a graph structure.
		(In other words, this connector does not expose as a graph the data in an existing database with an arbitrary schema.)
  </para>
	<para>
		The &JpaSource; class provides a number of JavaBean properties that control its behavior:
	</para>
	<table frame='all'>
		<title>&JpaSource; properties</title>
		<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
      <colspec colname='c1' colwidth="1*"/>
      <colspec colname='c2' colwidth="1*"/>
			<thead>
				<row>
		  		<entry>Property</entry>
		  		<entry>Description</entry>
				</row>
			</thead>
			<tbody>
				<row>
					<entry>autoGenerateSchema</entry>
					<entry>
			      Sets the Hibernate setting dictating what it does with the database schema upon first connection. Valid values are as
			      follows (though the value is not checked):
			      <itemizedlist>
			      <listitem><para>"<code>create</code>" - Create the database schema objects when the &EntityManagerFactory; is created (actually
			      when Hibernate's SessionFactory is created by the entity manager factory). If a file named "import.sql" exists in
			      the root of the class path (e.g., '/import.sql') Hibernate will read and execute the SQL statements in this file after it
			      has created the database objects. Note that Hibernate first delete all tables, constraints, or any other database object
			      that is going to be created in the process of building the schema.</para></listitem>
			      <listitem><para>"<code>create-drop</code>" - Same as "<code>create</code>", except that the schema will be dropped after the
			      &EntityManagerFactory; is closed.</para></listitem>
			      <listitem><para>"<code>update</code>" - Attempt to update the database structure to the current mapping (but does not read and invoke
			      the SQL statements from "import.sql"). <emphasis>Use with caution.</emphasis></para></listitem>
			      <listitem><para>"<code>validate</code>" - Validates the existing schema with the current entities configuration, but does not make any
			      changes to the schema (and does not read and invoke the SQL statements from "import.sql"). This is often the proper setting
			      to use in production, and thus this is the default value.</para></listitem>
			      </itemizedlist>
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>cacheTimeToLiveInMilliseconds</entry>
					<entry>Optional property that, if used, defines the maximum time in milliseconds that any information returned by this connector
						is allowed to be cached before being considered invalid.  When not used, this source will not define a specific
						duration for caching information.
						The default value is "600000" milliseconds, or 10 minutes.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>compressData</entry>
					<entry>
						An advanced boolean property that dictates whether large binary and string values should be stored in a compressed form.  
						This is enabled by default.  Setting this value only affects how new records are stored; records can always be read
						regardless of the value of this setting.
						The default value is "true".
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>creatingWorkspaceAllowed</entry>
					<entry>
						Optional property that defines whether clients can create additional workspaces.  The default value is "true".
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>dialect</entry>
					<entry>
						Optional property that defines the dialect of the database. If not provided, the dialect will be auto-discovered by Hibernate. 
						Otherwise, this must match one of the Hibernate dialect names, and must correspond to the type of driver being used.
						And because Hibernate does a good job of auto-determining the dialect, it is recommended that you set this only if auto-discovery fails
						for your database. (Note that auto-discovering the dialect does not always work well with MySQL, since Hibernate has multiple
						dialects for MySQL and will often choose  MySQL 4 MyISAM.)
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>dataSourceJndiName</entry>
					<entry>
						The JNDI name of the JDBC DataSource instance that should be used.  If not specified, the other driver properties must be set.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>driverClassloaderName</entry>
					<entry>
						The name of the <!-- link linkend="class_loader_factory" -->class loader or classpath<!--  /link --> that should be used to load the JDBC driver class.
						This is not required if the DataSource is found in JNDI.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>driverClassName</entry>
					<entry>
						The name of the JDBC driver class.
						This is not required if the DataSource is found in JNDI, but is required otherwise.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>idleTimeInSecondsBeforeTestingConnections</entry>
					<entry>
						The number of seconds after a connection remains in the pool that the connection should be tested to ensure it is still valid.
						The default is 180 seconds (or 3 minutes).
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
                                       <entry>isolationLevel</entry>
                                       <entry>Optional property that, if used, de
                                       of the java.sql.Connection#TRANSACTION_* c
                                       "TRANSACTION_READ_COMMITTED", "TRANSACTION
                                       not all JDBC drivers support all isolation
                                               When this property is not used, th
                                               isolation level is currently set o
                                       </entry>
                               </row>
                               <row>
					<entry>largeValueSizeInBytes</entry>
					<entry>
						An advanced boolean property that controls the size of property values at which they are considered to be "large values".  
						Depending upon the model, large property values may be stored in a centralized area and keyed by a secure hash
						of the value.  This is an space and performance optimization that stores each unique large value only once.
						The default value is "1024" bytes, or 1 kilobyte.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>maximumConnectionsInPool</entry>
					<entry>
						The maximum number of connections that may be in the connection pool.
						The default is "5".
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>maximumConnectionIdleTimeInSeconds</entry>
					<entry>
						The maximum number of seconds that a connection should remain in the pool before being closed.
						The default is "600" seconds (or 10 minutes).
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>maximumSizeOfStatementCache</entry>
					<entry>
						The maximum number of statements that should be cached.  
						Statement caching can be disabled by setting to "0".  
						The default is "100".
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>minimumConnectionsInPool</entry>
					<entry>
						The minimum number of connections that will be kept in the connection pool.
						The default is "0".
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>model</entry>
					<entry>
						An advanced property that dictates the type of storage schema that is used.  Currently, the only supported value is "Simple".  
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>name</entry>
					<entry>The name of the repository source, which is used by the &RepositoryService; when obtaining a &RepositoryConnection; by name.</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>nameOfDefaultWorkspace</entry>
					<entry>Optional property that is initialized to an empty string and which defines the name for the workspace that will be used by default
						if none is specified.</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>numberOfConnectionsToAcquireAsNeeded</entry>
					<entry>
						The number of connections that should be added to the pool when there are not enough to be used.
						The default is "1".
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>password</entry>
					<entry>
						The password that should be used when creating JDBC connections using the JDBC driver class.  
						This is not required if the DataSource is found in JNDI.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>predefinedWorkspaceNames</entry>
					<entry>Optional property that, if used, defines names of the workspaces that are predefined and need not be created before being used.
						This can be coupled with a "false" value for the "creatingWorkspaceAllowed" property to allow only the use of only predefined workspaces.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>retryLimit</entry>
					<entry>Optional property that, if used, defines the number of times that any single operation on a &RepositoryConnection; to this source should be retried
						following a communication failure. 
						The default value is '0'.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>rootNodeUuid</entry>
					<entry>Optional property that, if used, defines the UUID of the root node in the repository.  If not used,
						then a new UUID is generated.</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>updatesAllowed</entry>
					<entry>Determines whether the content in the database is can be updated ("true"), or if the content may only be read ("false").
						The default value is "true".</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>url</entry>
					<entry>
						The URL that should be used when creating JDBC connections using the JDBC driver class.
						This is not required if the DataSource is found in JNDI.
					</entry>
				</row>
				<row>
					<entry>username</entry>
					<entry>
						The username that should be used when creating JDBC connections using the JDBC driver class.
						This is not required if the DataSource is found in JNDI.
					</entry>
				</row>
			</tbody>
		</tgroup>
	</table>
 	<para>
		One way to configure the JPA connector is to create &JcrConfiguration; instance with a repository source that uses the &JpaSource; class.
		For example:
	</para>
  <programlisting language="JAVA" role="JAVA"><![CDATA[
JcrConfiguration config = ...
config.repositorySource("JPA Store")
      .usingClass(JpaSource.class)
      .setDescription("The database store for our content")
      .setProperty("dataSourceJndiName", "java:/MyDataSource")
      .setProperty("defaultWorkspaceName", "My Default Workspace")
      .setProperty("autoGenerateSchema", "validate");
 ]]></programlisting>
  	<para>
		Of course, setting other more advanced properties would entail calling <code>setProperty(...)</code> for each.  Since almost all
		of the properties have acceptable default values, however, we don't need to set very many of them.
	</para>
 	<para>
		Another way to configure the JPA connector is to create &JcrConfiguration; instance and load an XML configuration file that contains a repository source that 
		uses the &JpaSource; class.
		For example a file named configRepository.xml can be created with these contents:
	</para>
	
  <programlisting language="XML" role="XML"><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration xmlns:mode="http://www.modeshape.org/1.0" xmlns:jcr="http://www.jcp.org/jcr/1.0">
    <!-- 
    Define the sources for the content.  These sources are directly accessible using the 
    ModeShape-specific Graph API.  In fact, this is how the ModeShape JCR implementation works.  You 
    can think of these as being similar to JDBC DataSource objects, except that they expose 
    graph content via the Graph API instead of records via SQL or JDBC. 
    -->
    <mode:sources jcr:primaryType="nt:unstructured">
        <!-- 
        The 'JPA Store' repository is an JPA source with a single default workspace (though 
        others could be created, too).
        -->
        <mode:source jcr:name="JPA Store" 
                    mode:classname="org.modeshape.connector.store.jpa.JpaSource"
                    mode:description="The database store for our content"
                    mode:dataSourceJndiName="java:/MyDataSource"
                    mode:defaultWorkspaceName="default"
                    mode:autoGenerateSchema="validate"/>    
    </mode:sources>
    
	<!-- MIME type detectors and JCR repositories would be defined below --> 
</configuration>
 ]]></programlisting>
	<para>
		The configuration can then be loaded from Java like this:
	</para>
	
	<programlisting language="JAVA" role="JAVA"><![CDATA[
JcrConfiguration config = new JcrConfiguration().loadFrom("/configRepository.xml");
 ]]></programlisting>
	<para>
	ModeShape users who prefer not to give DDL privileges to the ModeShape database user for this connector can use the ModeShape JPA DDL generation 
	tool to create the proper DDL files for their database dialect.  This tool is packaged as a zip in  
	utils/modeshape-jpa-ddl-gen/target/distribution when the maven assemply profile -Passembly is run.   Unzip the contents and run the ddl-gen script with the following syntax:
	</para>
<programlisting>
ddl-gen.sh(.bat) -dialect &lt;dialect name&gt; -model &lt;model_name&gt; [-out &lt;path to output directory&gt;]
</programlisting>
	<para>
	The dialect and model parameters should match the value of the <code>dialect</code> and <code>model</code> properties specified for the
	JPA connector.  
	</para>
	<para>
	Running this executable will create two files in the output directory (or the current directory if no output directory
	was specified): create.modeshape-jpa-connector.ddl and drop.modeshape-jpa-connector.ddl.  The former contains the DDL to create or replace the tables,
	foreign keys, indices, and sequences needed by the JPA connector and the latter contains the DDL to drop any tables, foreign keys, indices, and 
	sequences needed by the JPA connector.
	</para>

	<sect1>
		<title>Simple Model</title>
		<para>
			This database schema model stores node properties as opaque records in the same row as transparent values like the node's namespace, local name, 
			and same-name-sibling index. Large property values are stored separately.
		</para>
		<para>
			The set of tables used in this model includes:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Workspaces - the set of workspaces and their names.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Namespaces - the set of namespace URIs used in paths, property names, and property values.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Nodes - the nodes in the repository, where each node and its properties are represented by a single record. This approach makes it
		 				possible to efficiently work with nodes containing large numbers of children, where adding and removing child nodes is largely
		 				independent of the number of children. Since the primary consumer of ModeShape graph information is the JCR layer, and the JCR layer always
		 				retrieves the nodes' properties for retrieved nodes, the properties have been moved in-row with the nodes.  Properties are still store
		 				in an opaque, serialized (and optionally compressed) form. 
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						Large values - property values larger than a certain size will be broken out into this table, where they are tracked by
						their SHA-1 has and shared by all properties that have that same value. The values are stored in a binary (and optionally
						compressed) form.  
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
	 					Subgraph - a working area for efficiently computing the space of a subgraph; see below
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
				 		Options - the parameters for this store's configuration (common to all models)
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<para>
		 This database model contains two tables that are used in an efficient mechanism to find all of the nodes in the subgraph below
		 a certain node. This process starts by creating a record for the subgraph query, and then proceeds by executing a join to find
		 all the children of the top-level node, and inserting them into the database (in a working area associated with the subgraph
		 query). Then, another join finds all the children of those children and inserts them into the same working area. This continues
		 until the maximum depth has been reached, or until there are no more children (whichever comes first). All of the nodes in the
		 subgraph are then represented by records in the working area, and can be used to quickly and efficient work with the subgraph
		 nodes. When finished, the mechanism deletes the records in the working area associated with the subgraph query.
		</para>
		<para>
		 This subgraph query mechanism is extremely efficient, performing one join/insert statement <emphasis>per level of the subgraph</emphasis>,
		 and is completely independent of the number of nodes in the subgraph. For example, consider a subgraph of node A, where A has
		 10 children, and each child contains 10 children, and each grandchild contains 10 children. This subgraph has a total of 1111
		 nodes (1 root + 10 children + 10*10 grandchildren + 10*10*10 great-grandchildren). Finding the nodes in this subgraph would
		 normally require 1 query per node (in other words, 1111 queries). But with this subgraph query mechanism, all of the nodes in
		 the subgraph can be found with 1 insert plus 4 additional join/inserts.
		</para>
		<para>
		 This mechanism has the added benefit that the set of nodes in the subgraph are kept in a working area in the database, meaning
		 they don't have to be pulled into memory.
		</para>
		<para>
		 In the Simple model, subgraph queries are used to efficiently process a number of different requests, including &ReadBranchRequest;
		 and &DeleteBranchRequest;. Processing each of these kinds of
		 requests requires knowledge of the subgraph, and in fact all but the &ReadBranchRequest; need to know the complete
		 subgraph.
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>

