<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ ModeShape (http://www.modeshape.org)
  ~
  ~ See the COPYRIGHT.txt file distributed with this work for information
  ~ regarding copyright ownership.  Some portions may be licensed
  ~ to Red Hat, Inc. under one or more contributor license agreements.
  ~ See the AUTHORS.txt file in the distribution for a full listing of 
  ~ individual contributors.
  ~
  ~ ModeShape is free software. Unless otherwise indicated, all code in ModeShape
  ~ is licensed to you under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as
  ~ published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of
  ~ the License, or (at your option) any later version.
  ~
  ~ ModeShape is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY
  ~ or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ for more details.
  ~
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ along with this distribution; if not, write to:
  ~ Free Software Foundation, Inc.
  ~ 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor
  ~ Boston, MA  02110-1301  USA
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % CustomDTD SYSTEM "../custom.dtd">
%CustomDTD;
]>
<chapter id="conclusion">
	<title>Wrapping Up</title>
	<para>
		This document provides a very high-level overview of ModeShape, introducing you to some basic concepts 
		and showing what would be required to use ModeShape in your own application.  
		We saw two simple examples that showed two different aspects of ModeShape: the sequencing system
		and the connector system.  Each of these examples showed how to create a ModeShape configuration, how to start up
		the ModeShape engine, and how to then access a <code>javax.jcr.Repository</code> instance, and after that your application
		just uses the standard JCR API.
	</para>
	<para>
		For a more in-depth description of ModeShape and the internal workings, see our &ReferenceGuide;.
		This also describes how to write your own custom sequencers or connectors.
    If you have any questions or comments, please feel free to contact ModeShape's
    <ulink url="mailto:modeshape-users@lists.jboss.org">user mailing list</ulink>, use our
    <ulink url="http://community.jboss.org/community/modeshape">discussion forums</ulink>,
    or chat with the developers in the <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/modeshape/chat.html">IRC chat room</ulink>.
    If you find a bug or have a suggestion, please let us know or (better yet) create a new issue in the project's
    <ulink url="&JIRA;">JIRA issue management system</ulink>
    . If there's something in particular you're interested in, talk with the community - there may be others interested in the
    same thing.
	</para>
	<sect1 id="future">
		<title>Future directions</title>
	  <para>
			Although ModeShape &versionNumber; includes several improvements and minor features, this release is primarily 
			a bug-fix release, with numerous fixes for issues reported against 2.1 and 2.2. For details,
			see the <ulink url="&ReleaseNotes;">release notes</ulink>.
		</para>
		<para><emphasis role="strong">ModeShape implements all of the required JCR 2.0 features</emphasis>: 
			repository acquisition, authentication, reading/navigating, query, export, node type discovery, and permissions and 
			capability checking. 
			<emphasis role="strong">ModeShape also implements most of the optional JCR 2.0 features</emphasis>:
			writing, import, observation, workspace management, versioning, locking, node type management, same-name siblings, 
			orderable child nodes, and shareable nodes.
			The remaining optional features (access control management, lifecycle management, 
			retention and hold, and transactions) may be introduced in future versions.
		</para>
		<para>
			Over the next few releases, we'll be adding more sequencers, connectors, and making a variety of improvements and bug fixes.
			Other items on our long-term roadmap include a web user interface, Seam integration, and integration with even more kinds of
			information systems and repositories.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="get_involved">
		<title>Getting involved</title>
		<para>
		  If you're interested in getting involved with the ModeShape project, take a look at our 
		  <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/modeshape/community.html">community pages</ulink>, 
		  and consider picking up one of the sequencers or connectors on our
		  <ulink url="&Roadmap;">roadmap</ulink>.
		  Or, check out <ulink url="&JIRA;">JIRA</ulink>
		  for the list of features we've thought of.  If you think of one that's not there, please add it to JIRA!
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
