<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ JBoss DNA (http://www.jboss.org/dna)
  ~
  ~ See the COPYRIGHT.txt file distributed with this work for information
  ~ regarding copyright ownership.  Some portions may be licensed
  ~ to Red Hat, Inc. under one or more contributor license agreements.
  ~ See the AUTHORS.txt file in the distribution for a full listing of 
  ~ individual contributors.
  ~
  ~ JBoss DNA is free software. Unless otherwise indicated, all code in JBoss DNA
  ~ is licensed to you under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as
  ~ published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of
  ~ the License, or (at your option) any later version.
  ~
  ~ JBoss DNA is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY
  ~ or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ for more details.
  ~
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ along with this distribution; if not, write to:
  ~ Free Software Foundation, Inc.
  ~ 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor
  ~ Boston, MA  02110-1301  USA
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="understanding_dna">
  <title>Understanding JBoss DNA</title>
  <sect1 id="jboss_dna_overview">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>JBoss DNA is a repository and set of tools that make it easy to capture, version, analyze, and understand the
      fundamental building blocks of information. As models, service and process definitions, schemas, source code, and other
      artifacts are added to the repository, JBoss DNA "sequences" the makeup of these components and extracts their structure
      and interdependencies. The JBoss DNA web application will allow end users to access, visualize, and edit this information in
      the terminology and structure they are familiar with. Such domain-specific solutions can be easily created with little or
      no programming.</para>
    <para> JBoss DNA supports the Java Content Repository (JCR) standard and is able to provide a single integrated view of
      multiple repositories, external databases, services, and applications, ensuring that JBoss DNA has access to the latest
      and most reliable master data. For instance, DNA could provide in a single view valuable insight into the business
      processes and process-level services impacted by a change to in an intermediary web server operation defined via WSDL.
      Similarly, a user could quickly view and navigate the dependencies between the data source models and transformation
      information stored within a content repository, the code base stored within a version control system, and the database
      schemas used by an application.</para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="architecture">
    <title>Architecture</title>
    <para>The planned architecture for JBoss DNA consists of several major components that will be built on top of standard APIs,
      including JCR, JDBC, JNDI and HTTP. The goal is to allow these components to be assembled as needed and add value on top
      of other DNA components or third-party systems that support these standard APIs.  Not all of these components exist
      yet - at the moment we're focusing on completing our JCR-compliant implementation using our connector framework.</para>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="dna-architecture.png" />
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata align="center" fileref="dna-architecture.png" />
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>
      Let's go over each of these components, starting from the bottom of the diagram:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">DNA Connectors</emphasis>
            are used to communicate with these external sources of information, whether there's one source (like a database) in
 						which all of the content is stored, or information is being federated from multiple sources.  The connector's
 						job is to interact with the external source and map the source's information into the lower-level graph language used by
						JBoss DNA.  Connectors also may optionally participate in distributed transactions by exposing an XAResource.
						In summary, then, the connector API isolates all of the other components from how the graph are persisted.
						We've built a number of connectors already, but we're always interested in adding more.  Or, you could write your own,
						since we've designed the connector API to be as straightforward as possible.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">DNA Federation</emphasis>
            is actually a special repository connector that accesses information from multiple other sources via connectors,
 						making all this information look like it is part of a single, unified repository.  Because it is a connector,
 						it can be used wherever connectors can be used.  And because it uses connectors, the federation connector
						makes it possible to integrate a wide variety of external systems, like other JCR
            repositories, databases, applications, and services.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">DNA JCR</emphasis>
            is an implementation of the JCR API that accesses the content from a single connector.  Our implementation has come a long
						way, and is nearly Level 1 and Level 2 compliant.  Finishing the remaining features, including search
						and query, are major objectives of our next release.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">DNA Sequencers</emphasis>
            are pluggable components that automatically process content (typically files) that are uploaded into the repository,
						looking for useful structure and information in that content.  When a file is uploaded to the repository, JBoss DNA automatically
						figures out which sequencer(s) should be run, and then runs them.  Each sequencer, then, extracts the meaningful information
						from the file's content and places that structure in the repository.  Once this information is in
            the repository, it can be viewed, edited, analyzed, searched, and related to other content. DNA defines a Java
            interface that sequencers must implement. DNA sequencers operate upon any JCR-compliant repository.
						We have a number of sequencers, but plan on adding more over time.  Like connectors, the Sequencer API makes it very
						simple to write sequencers for your own file types.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">DNA Analyses</emphasis>
            are similar to sequencers, except they process the graph structure rather than uploaded files.  You can think of them
 						as report generators, where they process some area of the repository and generate output.  The output doesn't take the
						form of a document or file, but rather more graph content that is then stored in the repository, where it can be accessed
						and searched just like any other content.  We're still figuring out how to best make analyzers easy to write and use,
						and have been focused on other aspects of the architecture.  But we're planning on using analyzers for dependency,
						similarity, and statistical analyses.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">DNA Maven</emphasis>
            is a classloader library compatible with Maven 2 project dependencies. This allows the creation of Java ClassLoader
            instances using Maven 2 style paths, and all dependencies are transitively managed and included.  This exists but is
						still immature.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
		<para>
			The remaining parts of the architecture haven't yet been started, but they service important purposes for a complete metadata
			repository system.
			<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">DNA Eclipse Plugins</emphasis>
            enable Eclipse users to access the contents of a JBoss DNA repository.  This is a planned component that may be started soon.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">DNA JDBC Driver</emphasis>
            provides a driver implementation, allowing JDBC-aware applications to connect to and use a JBoss DNA repository.
            This is a planned component on our roadmap.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">DNA Remote JCR</emphasis>
            is a client-side component for accessing remote JCR repositories.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">DNA Web Application</emphasis>
            is used by end users and domain experts to visualize, search, edit, change and tag the repository content. The web
            application uses views to define how different types of information are to be presented and edited in
            domain-specific ways. The goal is that this web application is easily customized and branded for inclusion into
            other solutions and application systems. The DNA Web Application operates upon any JCR-compliant repository,
            although it does rely upon the DNA analysis and templating services.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">DNA Publishing Server</emphasis>
            allows content to be downloaded, uploaded, and edited using the Atom Publishing Protocol. With the DNA Publishing
            Server, the content of the repository can easily be created, read, edited, and deleted using the standard HTTP
            operations of POST, GET, PUT, and DELETE (respectively). More and more tools are being created that support working
            with Atom Publishing servers. The DNA Publishing Server operates upon any JCR-compliant repository.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">DNA WebDAV Server</emphasis>
            allows clients such as Microsoft Windows and Apple OS X to connect to, read, and edit the content in the repository
            using the WebDAV standard. WebDAV is an extension of HTTP, so web browsers are able to access the content 
            served by a WebDAV compliant server. The DNA WebDAV Server operates upon any JCR-compliant repository.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">DNA Views</emphasis>
            are definitions of how types of information are to be presented in a user interface to allow for creation, reading,
            editing, and deletion of information. DNA view definitions consist of data stored in a JCR repository, and as such
            views can be easily added, changed or removed entirely by using the DNA Web Application, requiring no programming.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      Continue reading the rest of this chapter for more detail about the
      <link linkend="sequencers">sequencing framework</link> available in this release, or the <link linkend="federation">federation engine</link>
      and <link linkend="federation_connectors">connectors</link>. Or, skip to the <link linkend="downloading_and_running">examples</link>
      to see how to start using JBoss DNA &versionNumber; today. 
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="sequencers">
    <title>Sequencing content</title>
    <para> The current JBoss DNA release contains a sequencing framework that is designed to sequence data (typically files)
      stored in a JCR repository to automatically extract meaningful and useful information. This additional information is then
      saved back into the repository, where it can be accessed and used.</para>
    <para> In other words, you can just upload various kinds of files into a JCR repository, and DNA automatically processes
      those files to extract meaningful structured information. For example, load DDL files into the repository, and let
      sequencers extract the structure and metadata for the database schema. Load Hibernate configuration files into the
      repository, and let sequencers extract the schema and mapping information. Load Java source into the repository, and let
      sequencers extract the class structure, JavaDoc, and annotations. Load a PNG, JPEG, or other image into the repository,
      and let sequencers extract the metadata from the image and save it in the repository. The same with XSDs, WSDL, WS
      policies, UML, MetaMatrix models, etc.</para>
    <para>
      JBoss DNA sequencers sit on top of existing JCR repositories (including federated repositories) - they basically extract
      more useful information from what's already stored in the repository. And they use the existing JCR event and versioning system. Each
      sequencer typically processes a single kind of file format or a single kind of content. </para>
    <para>The following sequencers are included in JBoss DNA:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Image sequencer</emphasis>
            - A sequencer that processes the binary content of an image file, extracts the metadata for the image, and then
            writes that image metadata to the repository. It gets the file format, image resolution, number of bits per pixel
            (and optionally number of images), comments and physical resolution from JPEG, GIF, BMP, PCX, PNG, IFF, RAS, PBM,
            PGM, PPM, and PSD files. (This sequencer may be improved in the future to also extract EXIF metadata from JPEG
            files; see <ulink url="http://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/DNA-26">DNA-26</ulink>.)
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">MP3 sequencer</emphasis>
            - A sequencer that processes the contents of an MP3 audio file, extracts the metadata for the file, and then
            writes that image metadata to the repository. It gets the title, author, album, year, and comment.  
            (This sequencer may be improved in the future to also extract other ID3 metadata from other audio file formats; see
            <ulink url="http://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/DNA-66">DNA-66</ulink>.)
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">ZIP Archive Sequencer</emphasis>
            - Process ZIP archive files to extract (explode) the contents into the repository.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Java Source File Sequencer</emphasis>
            - Process Java source files to extract the class structure (including annotations) into the repository.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">XML File Sequencer</emphasis>
            - Process XML files to extract the structure into the repository.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Microsoft Office File Sequencer</emphasis>
            - Process Microsoft Office documents, spreadsheets, and presentation files to extract their basic structure.
						For example, the sequencer extracts the outline of a document, or the title and outline of a presentation. 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">JCR Compact Node Definition (CND) File Sequencer</emphasis>
            - Process the CND files defined by JCR, extracting the various node types with their property definitions and child
						node definitions.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      As the community develops additional sequencers, they will also be included in JBoss DNA. Some of those that have been
      identified as being useful include:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Data Definition Language (DDL) Sequencer</emphasis>
            - Process various dialects of DDL, including that from Oracle, SQL Server, MySQL, PostgreSQL, and others. May need
            to be split up into a different sequencer for each dialect. This sequencer is being developed as part of a
						Google Summer of Code 2009 project. (See
            <ulink url="http://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/DNA-26">DNA-26</ulink>
            )
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">XML Schema Document (XSD) Sequencer</emphasis>
            - Process XSD files and extract the various elements, attributes, complex types, simple types, groups, and other
            information. (See
            <ulink url="http://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/DNA-32">DNA-32</ulink>
            )
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Web Service Definition Language (WSDL) Sequencer</emphasis>
            - Process WSDL files and extract the services, bindings, ports, operations, parameters, and other information. (See
            <ulink url="http://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/DNA-33">DNA-33</ulink>
            )
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Hibernate File Sequencer</emphasis>
            - Process Hibernate configuration (cfg.xml) and mapping (hbm.xml) files to extract the configuration and mapping
            information. (See
            <ulink url="http://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/DNA-61">DNA-61</ulink>
            )
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">XML Metadata Interchange (XMI) Sequencer</emphasis>
            - Process XMI documents that contain UML models or models using another metamodel, extracting the model structure
            into the repository. (See
            <ulink url="http://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/DNA-31">DNA-31</ulink>
            )
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Java Archive (JAR) Sequencer</emphasis>
            - Process JAR files to extract (explode) the contents into the classes and file resources. (See
            <ulink url="http://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/DNA-64">DNA-64</ulink>
            )
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Java Class File Sequencer</emphasis>
            - Process Java class files (bytecode) to extract the class structure (including annotations) into the repository.
            (See
            <ulink url="http://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/DNA-62">DNA-62</ulink>
            )
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">PDF Sequencer</emphasis>
            - Process PDF files to extract the document metadata, including table of contents. (See
            <ulink url="http://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/DNA-50">DNA-50</ulink>
            )
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Maven 2 POM Sequencer</emphasis>
            - Process Maven 2 Project Object Model (POM) files to extract the project information, dependencies, plugins, and
            other content. (See
            <ulink url="http://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/DNA-24">DNA-24</ulink>
            )
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">MP3 and MP4 Sequencer</emphasis>
            - Process MP3 and MP4 audio files to extract the name of the song, artist, album, track number, and other metadata.
            (See
            <ulink url="http://jira.jboss.org/jira/browse/DNA-30">DNA-30</ulink>
            )
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </para>
    <para>
      The
      <link linkend="using_dna">examples</link>
      in this book go into more detail about how sequencers are managed and used, and
      <link linkend="custom_sequencers">Chapter 5</link>
      goes into detail about how to write custom sequencers.
    </para>
  </sect1>
  <sect1 id="federation">
    <title>JCR and federated repositories</title>
    <para>There is a lot of information stored in many of different places: databases, repositories, SCM systems,
      registries, file systems, services, etc. The purpose of the federation engine is to allow applications to use the JCR API
      to access that information as if it were all stored in a single JCR repository, but to really leave the information where
      it is.</para>
    <para>Why not just copy or move the information into a JCR repository?  Moving it is probably pretty difficult, since most 
			likely existing applications rely upon that information being where it is.  All of those applications
			would break or have to change.  And copying the information means that we'd have to continually synchronize the changes.
			This not only is a lot of work, but it often creates issues with knowing which information is accurate.
		</para>
    <para>The JBoss DNA allows lets us leave the information where it is, yet provide access to that information to new applications through
			the JCR API.  As the existing applications update the information in the original systems, applications using JBoss DNA also see
			these updates.  JCR clients	even get the benefit of using JCR observation to be notified of the changes.  And if a JBoss DNA repository is
      configured to allow updates, client applications can change the information in the repository and JBoss DNA will propagate
      those changes down to the original source.</para>
    <sect2 id="repository-connectors">
      <title>Connecting to information sources</title>
      <para>
        JBoss DNA uses connectors to interact with different information sources to get at the content
        in those systems. We already have some connectors, including:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">In-Memory Connector</emphasis>
            - Uses a Map instance as a repository. This is a simple connector that works really well for small and transient graphs.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">JBoss Cache Connector</emphasis>
            - Uses a JBoss Cache instance as a repository.  JBoss Cache is a powerful cache capable of persisting the information
 						and being clustered for concurrent use by multiple processes.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Federation Connector</emphasis>
            - Creates a single repository by accessing and federating the information in multiple other repository sources.
						This is a powerful connector that is discussed in more detail in the <link linkend="federated_repositories">next section</link>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">File System Connector</emphasis>
            - Expose the files and directories on a file system through JCR.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">JPA-based Storage Connector</emphasis>
            - Store and access information in a relational database through JPA. Also useful for persisting information in the federated
            repository not stored elsewhere.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
			<para>We're working on a few other connectors:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">JDBC Metadata Connector</emphasis>
            - Connect to relational databases via JDBC and expose their schema as content in a repository.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">SVN Connector</emphasis>
            - Interact with Subversion software configuration management (SCM) repositories to expose the managed resources
            through JCR. Consider using the
            <ulink url="http://svnkit.com/">SVNkit</ulink>
            (dual license) library for an API into Subversion.
          </para>
        </listitem>        
      </itemizedlist>
			<para>And even more connectors that are planned:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">JCR Repository Connector</emphasis>
            - Connect to and interact with other JCR repositories.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Maven 2 Repository Connector</emphasis>
            - Access and expose the contents of a Maven 2 repository (either on the local file system or via HTTP) through
            JCR.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">UDDI Connector</emphasis>
            - Interact with UDDI registries to integrate their content into a repository.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">CVS Connector</emphasis>
            - Interact with CVS software configuration management (SCM) repositories to expose the managed resources through
            JCR.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis role="strong">Distributed Database Connector</emphasis>
            - Store and access information in a
            <ulink url="http://www.hypertable.org/">Hypertable</ulink>
            or
            <ulink url="http://hadoop.apache.org/hbase/">HBase</ulink>
            distributed databases. Also useful for persisting information in the federated repository not stored elsewhere.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>
        If the connectors allow the information they contribute to be updated, they must provide an
        <code>XAResource</code>
        implementation that can be used with a Java Transaction Service. Connectors that provide read-only access need not
        provide an implementation.
      </para>
      <para>
        Also, connectors talk to
        <emphasis>sources</emphasis>
        of information, and it's quite likely that the same connector is used to talk to different sources. Each source contains
        the configuration details (e.g., connection information, location, properties, options, etc.) for working with that
        particular source, as well as a reference to the connector that should be used to establish connections to the source.
        And of course, sources can be added or removed without having to stop and restart the federated repository.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="federated_repositories">
      <title>Federated repositories</title>
      <para> The federation connector works by effectively building up a single graph by querying each source and merging or
        unifying the responses. This information is cached, which improves performance, reduces the number of (potentially
        expensive) remote calls, reduces the load on the sources, and helps mitigate problems with source availability. As
        clients interact with the repository, this cache is consulted first. When the requested portion of the graph (or
        "subgraph") is contained completely in the cache, it is retuned immediately. However, if any part of the requested
        subgraph is not in the cache, each source is consulted for their contributions to that subgraph, and any results are
        cached.</para>
      <para> This basic flow makes it possible for the federated repository to build up a local cache of the integrated graph
        (or at least the portions that are used by clients). In fact, the federated repository caches information in a manner
        that is similar to that of the Domain Name System (DNS). As sources are consulted for their contributions, the source
        also specifies whether it is the authoritative source for this information (some sources that are themselves federated
        may not be the information's authority), whether the information may be modified, the time-to-live (TTL) value (the time
        after which the cached information should be refreshed), and the expiration time (the time after which the cached
        information is no longer valid). In effect, the source has complete control over how the information it contributes is
        cached and used.</para>
      <para>
        The federated repository also needs to incorporate
        <emphasis>negative caching</emphasis>
        , which is storage of the knowledge that something does not exist. Sources can be configured to contribute information
        only below certain paths (e.g.,
        <code>/A/B/C</code>
        ), and the federation engine can take advantage of this by never consulting that source for contributions to information
        on other paths. However, below that path, any negative responses must also be cached (with appropriate TTL and expiry
        parameters) to prevent the exclusion of that source (in case the source has information to contribute at a later time)
        or the frequent checking with the source.
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="federation_queries">
      <title>Searching and querying</title>
      <para> The JBoss DNA federated repository will support queries against the integrated and unified graph. In some
        situations the query can be determined to apply to a single source, but in most situations the query must be planned
        (and possibly rewritten) such that it can be pushed down to all the appropriate sources. Also, the cached results must
        be consulted prior to returning the query results, as the results from one source might have contributions from another
        source.</para>
      <para>Searching the whole federated repository is also important. This allows users to simply supply a handful of
        search terms, and to get results that are ranked based upon how close each result is to the search terms. (Searching is
        very different from querying, which involves specifying the exact semantics of what is to be searched and how the
        information is to be compared.) JBoss DNA will incorporate a search engine (e.g., likely to be Lucene) and will populate
        the engine's indexes using the federated content and the cached information. Notifications of changing information will
        be reflected in the indexes, but some sources may want to explicitly allow or disallow periodic crawling of their
        content.</para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="federation_updates">
      <title>Updating content</title>
      <para>
        The JBoss DNA federated repositories also make it possible for client applications to make changes to the unified graph
        within the context of distributed transactions. According to the JCR API, client applications use the Java Transaction
        API (JTA) to control the boundaries of their transactions. Meanwhile, the federated repository uses a
        <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/jbosstm/">distributed transaction service</ulink>
        to coordinate the XA resources provided by the connectors.
      </para>
      <para> It is quite possible that clients add properties to nodes in the unified graph, and that this information cannot be
        handled by the same underlying source that contributed to the node. In this case, the federated repository can be
        configured with a fallback source that will be used used to store this "extra" information.</para>
      <para>
        It is a goal that non-XA sources (i.e., sources that use connectors without XA resources) can participate in distributed
        transactions through the use of
        <emphasis>compensating transactions</emphasis>
        . Because the JBoss DNA federation engine implements the JCR observation system, it is capable of recording all of the
        changes made to the distributed graph (and those changes sent to each updatable source). Therefore, if a non-XA source
        is involved in a distributed transaction that must be rolled back, any changes made to non-XA sources can be undone. (Of
        course, this does not make the underlying source transactional: non-transactional sources still may expose the interim
        changes to other clients.)
      </para>
    </sect2>
    <sect2 id="federation_events">
      <title>Observing changes</title>
      <para> The JCR API supports observing a repository to receive notifications of additions, changes and deletions of nodes
        and properties. The JBoss DNA federated repository will support this API through two primary means.</para>
      <para> When the changes are made through the federated repository, the JBoss DNA federation engine is well aware of the
        set of changes that have been (or are being) made to the unified graph. These events are directly propagated to
        listeners.</para>
      <para> Sources have the ability to publish events, making it possible for the JBoss DNA federation engine and clients that
        have registered listeners to be notified of changes in the information managed by that source. These events are first
        processed by the federation engine and possibly altered based upon contributions from other sources. (The federation
        engine also uses these events to update or purge information in the cache, which may add to the event set.) The
        resulting (and possibly altered) event set is then sent to all client listeners.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
</chapter>
