<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ ModeShape (http://www.modeshape.org)
  ~
  ~ See the COPYRIGHT.txt file distributed with this work for information
  ~ regarding copyright ownership.  Some portions may be licensed
  ~ to Red Hat, Inc. under one or more contributor license agreements.
  ~ See the AUTHORS.txt file in the distribution for a full listing of 
  ~ individual contributors.
  ~
  ~ ModeShape is free software. Unless otherwise indicated, all code in ModeShape
  ~ is licensed to you under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as
  ~ published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of
  ~ the License, or (at your option) any later version.
  ~
  ~ ModeShape is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY
  ~ or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ for more details.
  ~
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ along with this distribution; if not, write to:
  ~ Free Software Foundation, Inc.
  ~ 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor
  ~ Boston, MA  02110-1301  USA
  -->
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd	" [
<!ENTITY % CustomDTD SYSTEM "../custom.dtd">
%CustomDTD;
]>
<chapter id="using_modeshape">
	<title>Using ModeShape</title>
	<para>Using ModeShape within your application is actually quite straightforward.  Although there are multiple ways to 
		access a JCR repository in ModeShape, the simplest is to use the <ulink url="&JSR283;">JSR-283</ulink> &RepositoryFactory; interface to 
		get a reference to a named &Repository; from a configuration file.  After that, you continue to work with your repository content using the JCR API.
	</para>
	<sect1 id="repository_factory">
		<title>ModeShape's RepositoryFactory</title>
		<para>
			ModeShape provides an implementation of the &RepositoryFactory; interface that can return a reference to a named repository
			based on a provided configuration file.  The code to get started with this is very simple.
		</para>
    <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[
String configUrl = ... ; // URL that points to your configuration file
Map params = Collections.singletonMap("org.modeshape.jcr.URL", configUrl);
Repository repository;

for (RepositoryFactory factory : ServiceLoader.load(RepositoryFactory.class)) {
    repository = factory.getRepository(parameters);
    if (repository != null) break;
}]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			This code looks for all &RepositoryFactory; implementations on the classpath (assuming those implementations properly defined the service provider
			within their JARs), and will ask each to create a repository given the supplied parameters. Thus, the parameters
			are specific to the implementation you want to use.
	  </para>
		<note>
			<para>
				With JCR 1.0, applications could only find a &Repository; instance using implementation-specific code.
				This new JCR 2.0 approach is a bit more complicated, but should work with most JCR 2.0 implementations
				and does not require using any implementation classes. And your application can even load the parameters
				from a configuration resource, meaning nothing in your application depends on a particular JCR implementation.
			</para>
		</note>
	  <para>
			ModeShape uses a single property named "<code>org.modeshape.jcr.URL</code>"
			with a value that is a URL that either resolves to a ModeShape configuration file, such as
	  </para>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[ file://path/to/configFile.xml?repositoryName=MyRepository ]]></programlisting>
    <para>
	    that references a file on the local file system, or
	  </para>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[ classpath:path/to/configFile.xml?repositoryName=MyRepository ]]></programlisting>
    <para>
	    that references a file on the local classpath, or
	  </para>
    <programlisting><![CDATA[ jndi://name/in/jndi?repositoryName=MyRepository ]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			to point to an existing &Repositories; or &JcrEngine; instance registered in JNDI.
			Pointing directly to a configuration file often works well in stand-alone applications, while using JNDI works great
			for applications deployed to server platforms (e.g., an application server or servlet container) where multiple applications
			might want to use the same JCR repository while hiding all of the configuration details from the JCR clients. 
			We'll see in the <link linkend="jcr_engine">next section</link> 
			how to configure ModeShape's &JcrEngine; explicitly and register it in JNDI.
		</para>
		<para>
			So, here's the ServiceLoader example again, but with ModeShape-specific parameters:
		</para>
    <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[String configUrl = ... ; // URL that points to your configuration file
Map<String,String> parameters = Collections.singletonMap("org.modeshape.jcr.URL", configUrl);

Repository repository = null;
for (RepositoryFactory factory : ServiceLoader.load(RepositoryFactory.class)) {
    repository = factory.getRepository(parameters);
    if (repository != null) break;
}]]></programlisting>
		<para>
			Once you've gotten hold of a &Repository; instance, you can use it to create &Session;s, using code similar to:
    </para>			
    <programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[Credentials credentials = ...; // JCR credentials
String workspaceName = ...;  // Name of repository workspace
Session session = repository.login(credentials,workspaceName);
]]></programlisting>
		</sect1>
	<sect1 id="jcr_configuration">
		<title>ModeShape Configuration Files</title>
		<para>
			The previous section showed how easy it was to obtain a Repository and Session using the standard JCR API, using
			a URL to point to an existing configuration file. This section provides an introduction to ModeShape configuration
			files, although you will likely want to look at the &ReferenceGuide; for a more detailed explanation.
		</para>
		<para>
			Each configuration file defines the components that are used to create the repository:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="strong"><code>Repository sources</code></emphasis> are the POJO objects that each describe a particular
					location where content is stored.  Each repository source object is an instance of a ModeShape connector, and is configured
					with the properties that particular source.  ModeShape's &RepositorySource; classes are analogous to JDBC's &DataSource; classes -
					they are implemented by specific connectors (aka, "drivers") for specific kinds of repository sources (aka, "databases").
					Similarly, a &RepositorySource; instance is analogous to a &DataSource; instance, with bean properties for each configurable
					parameter.  Therefore, each repository source definition must supply the name of the &RepositorySource; class, any
					bean properties, and, optionally, the classpath that should be used to load the class. </para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="strong"><code>Repositories</code></emphasis> define the JCR repositories that are available.  Each
					repository has a unique name that is used to obtain the &Repository; instance,
					but each repository definition also can include the predefined namespaces (other than those automatically defined by
					ModeShape), various options, and the node types that are to be available in the repository without explicit registration
					through the JCR API.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="strong"><code>Sequencers</code></emphasis> define the particular sequencers that are available for use.
					Each sequencer definition provides the path expressions governing which nodes in the repository should be sequenced when those nodes change,
					and where the resulting output generated by the sequencer should be placed.  The definition also must state the name of 
					the sequencer class, any bean properties and, optionally, the classpath that should be used to load the class.</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis role="strong"><code>MIME type detectors</code></emphasis> define the particular MIME type detector(s) that should
					be made available.  A MIME type detector does exactly what the name implies: it attempts to determine the MIME type given a
					"filename" and contents.  ModeShape automatically uses a detector that uses the file extension to identify the MIME type,
					but also provides an implementation that uses an external library to identify the MIME type based upon the contents.
					The definition must state the name of the detector class, any bean properties and, optionally, the classpath that should 
					be used to load the class.</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</para>
		<sect2 id="creating_a_configuration_file">
			<title>Creating a configuration file</title>
			<para>
				Creating a ModeShape configuration file is fairly straightforward.
				Here is the configuration file that is used in the repository example, though it has been simplified a bit and most comments 
				have been removed for clarity):
			</para>
    	<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<configuration xmlns:mode="http://www.modeshape.org/1.0" xmlns:jcr="http://www.jcp.org/jcr/1.0">
	  <!-- 
	  Define the JCR repositories 
	  -->
	  <mode:repositories>
	      <!-- 
	      Define a JCR repository that accesses the 'Cars' source directly.
	      -->
	      <mode:repository jcr:name="car repository" mode:source="Cars">
	          <mode:options jcr:primaryType="mode:options">
                <systemSourceName jcr:primaryType="mode:option" mode:value="system@Cars"/>
	              <jaasLoginConfigName jcr:primaryType="mode:option" mode:value="modeshape-jcr"/>
	              <!--
	              As a convenience, ModeShape defaults to granting guest users full access.  
	              In a production system, you would want to limit this access by uncommenting one of the 
	              options below:
	              
	              for no access:
	              <anonymousUserRoles jcr:PrimaryType="mode:option" mode:value="" />
	              
	              for read-only acces:
	              <anonymousUserRoles jcr:PrimaryType="mode:option" mode:value="readonly" /> 
	              -->
	          </mode:options>
	      </mode:repository>
	  </mode:repositories>
    <!-- 
    Define the sources for the content.  These sources are directly accessible using the ModeShape-specific 
    Graph API.
    -->
    <mode:sources jcr:primaryType="nt:unstructured">
        <mode:source jcr:name="Cars" 
                    mode:classname="org.modeshape.graph.connector.inmemory.InMemoryRepositorySource" 
                    mode:retryLimit="3" mode:defaultWorkspaceName="workspace1">
            <predefinedWorkspaceNames>system</predefinedWorkspaceNames>
        </mode:source>
    </mode:sources>
    <!-- 
    Define the sequencers. This is an optional section. 
    -->
    <mode:sequencers>
        <mode:sequencer jcr:name="Image Sequencer" 
                       mode:classname="org.modeshape.sequencer.image.ImageMetadataSequencer">
            <mode:description>Image metadata sequencer</mode:description>        
            <mode:pathExpression>/foo/source => /foo/target</mode:pathExpression>
            <mode:pathExpression>/bar/source => /bar/target</mode:pathExpression>
        </mode:sequencer>
    </mode:sequencers>
    <!--
	  Define how ModeShape will determine the MIME type of files. This is an optional section;
	  if you do not specify a MIME type detector, ModeShape will use a built-in one that is based
	  filename extensions for most commonly-used files.
    -->
    <mode:mimeTypeDetectors>
        <mode:mimeTypeDetector jcr:name="Detector" 
                 mode:description="Standard extension-based MIME type detector"/>
    </mode:mimeTypeDetectors>
</configuration>]]></programlisting>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="modeshape_and_jndi">
		<title>Deploying ModeShape via JNDI</title>
		<para>
			Sometimes your applications can simply define a configuration file and use the &RepositoryFactory; to access its
			repositories.
			This is very straightforward, and this is useful for many simple applications.
		</para>
		<para>
			Web applications are a different story. Often, you may not want your web application to contain the code that initializes
			a ModeShape JCR repository.  Or, you may want the same repository instance to be reused in multiple web applications deployed 
			to the same web/application server. In these cases, it is possible to configure the web/app server's JNDI instance to
			instantiate the repository, meaning the web applications need only use the standard JNDI and JCR APIs.
		</para>
		<sect2 id="modeshape_and_jndi_application">
			<title>Example application using JCR and JNDI</title>
			<para>
				Here's an example of how such a web application would obtain a JCR &Repository; instance, use it to create a &JcrSession;,
				and then close the session when completed.  
			</para>
    	<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[Session session = null;
try {
  // Look up the JCR Repository object ...
	InitialContext initCtx = new InitialContext();
	Context envCtx = (Context) initCtx.lookup("java:comp/env");
	Repository repo = (Repository) envCtx.lookup("jcr/local");		// name in JNDI is defined by configuration
	
	// Obtain a JCR Session using simple authentication
	// (or use anonymous authentication if desired)
	session = repo.login(new SimpleCredentials("username", "password".toCharArray()));
	
	// Use the JCR Session to do something interesting
	
} catch (Exception ex) {
	ex.printStackTrace();
} finally {
	if (session != null) session.logout();
}]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				Note that the location of the &Repository; instance in JNDI depends upon the configuration. In this example, we used
				"<code>jcr/local</code>", but the only requirement is that it match the location where it was placed in JNDI.
			</para>
			<para>
				We showed how web applications can use an existing &Repository; instance. In the next section, we describe how to configure
				the web server so that the &Repository; instance is available in JNDI.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="modeshape_and_jndi_configuring">
			<title>Configuring JCR and JNDI</title>
			<para>
				Each kind of web server or application server is different, but all servlet containers do provide a way of configuring
				objects and placing them into JNDI.  ModeShape provides a &JndiRepositoryFactory; class that implements &ObjectFactory;
				and that can be used in the server's configuration. The &JndiRepositoryFactory; requires two properties:
				<itemizedlist>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis role="strong"><code>configFile</code></emphasis> is the path to the 
							<link linkend="loading_from_file">configuration file</link> resource, which must be available on the classpath
						</para>
					</listitem>
					<listitem>
						<para>
							<emphasis role="strong"><code>repositoryName</code></emphasis> is the name of a JCR repository that exists
							in the JCR configuration and that will be made available by this JNDI entry
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</itemizedlist>
			</para>
			<para>
				Here's an example of a fragment of the <code>conf/context.xml</code> for Tomcat:
			</para>
<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<Resource name="jcr/local" 
          auth="Container"
          type="javax.jcr.Repository"
          factory="org.modeshape.jcr.JndiRepositoryFactory"
          configFile="/resource/path/to/configuration.xml"
          repositoryName="Test Repository Source" />]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				Note that it is possible to have multiple <code>Resource</code> entries. The &JndiRepositoryFactory; ensures
				that only one &JcrEngine; is instantiated, but that a &Repository; instance is registered for each entry.
			</para>
			<para>
				Before the server can start, however, all of the ModeShape jars need to be placed on the classpath for the server.
				JAAS also needs to be configured, and this can be done using the application server's configuration or in your
				web application if you're using a simple servlet container. For more details, see the &ReferenceGuide;.
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
					The ModeShape community has solicited input on how we can make it easier to consume and use ModeShape in applications
					that do not use Maven. Check out the <ulink url="http://community.jboss.org/thread/146589">discussion thread</ulink>,
					and please add any suggestions or opinions!
				</para>
			</note>
			<para>
				Then, your web application needs to reference the <code>Resource</code> and state its requirements in its 
				<code>web.xml</code>:
			</para>
<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<resource-env-ref>
   <description>Repository</description>
   <resource-env-ref-name>jcr/local</resource-env-ref-name>
   <resource-env-ref-type>javax.jcr.Repository</resource-env-ref-type>
</resource-env-ref>]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				Note that the value of <code>resource-env-ref-name</code> matches the value of the name attribute on the 
				<code>&lt;Resource></code> tag in the <code>context.xml</code> described above.  This is a must.
			</para>
			<para>
				At this point, your web application can perform the lookup of the &Repository; object, create and use a &Session;,
				and then close the &Session;.  Here's an example of a JSP page that does this:
			</para>
<programlisting role="JAVA"><![CDATA[
<%@ page import="javax.naming.*, javax.jcr.*, org.jboss.security.config.IDTrustConfiguration" %>
<%!

static {
	// Initialize IDTrust
	IDTrustConfiguration idtrustConfig = new IDTrustConfiguration();
	try {
	    idtrustConfig.config("security/jaas.conf.xml");
	} catch (Exception ex) {
	    throw new IllegalStateException(ex);
	}
}
%>
<%
Session sess = null;
try {
	InitialContext initCtx = new InitialContext();
	Context envCtx = (Context) initCtx.lookup("java:comp/env");
	Repository repo = (Repository) envCtx.lookup("jcr/local");
	sess = repo.login(new SimpleCredentials("readwrite", "readwrite".toCharArray()));

	// Do something interesting with the Session ...
	out.println(sess.getRootNode().getPrimaryNodeType().getName());
} catch (Exception ex) {
	ex.printStackTrace();
} finally {
	if (sess != null) sess.logout();
}
%>
]]></programlisting>			
			<para>
				Since this uses a servlet container, there is no JAAS implementation configured, so note the 
				loading of IDTrust to create the JAAS realm.  (To make this work in Tomcat, the security
				folder that contains the <code>jaas.conf.xml</code>, <code>users.properties</code>, and
				<code>roles.properties</code> needs to be moved into the <code>%CATALINA_HOME%</code> directory.)
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
				If you use an application server such as <ulink url="http://www.jboss.com/products/platforms/application/">JBoss EAP</ulink>,
				you could just configure the JAAS realm as part of the server configuration and be done with it.
			  </para>
			</note>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="modeshape_classpath">
		<title>Setting the Classpath</title>
		<para>
			Before you deploy ModeShape into your application or its environment, you need to make sure that all of the ModeShape
			JARs are on the appropriate classpath. Two different scenarios are covered in this section: Maven-based, and using
			JARs with the traditional classpath.
		</para>
		<sect2 id="using_modeshape_via_maven">
			<title>Building against ModeShape via Maven</title>
			<para>
				By far the easiest way to use ModeShape is to use Maven, because with just a few lines of code, Maven will automatically 
				pull all the JARs and source for all of the ModeShape libraries as well as everything those libraries need. 
				All of ModeShape's artifacts for each release are published in the new <ulink url="&JBossMaven;">JBoss Maven repository</ulink> 
				under the "<ulink url="&ModeShapeMaven;">org.modeshape</ulink>" group ID.
			</para>
			<sect3 id="using_jboss_maven_repository">
				<title>Using the JBoss Maven repository</title>
				<para>
					The JBoss Maven repository not only contains all of the artifacts for ModeShape and other open source projects
					hosted at <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org">JBoss.org</ulink>, but it also 
					<ulink url="&JBossMavenDoc;">proxies quite a few other repositories</ulink> that contain many other third-party
					libraries.
				</para>
				<para>
				  So if you're using Maven (or Ivy), first make sure your project knows about this new JBoss Maven repository.
					One way to do this is to add the following to your project POM (you'll still likely want to use other Maven repositories 
					for third-party artifacts):
				</para>
<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<repositories>
  <repository>
    <id>jboss</id>
    <url>http://repository.jboss.org/nexus/content/groups/public/</url>
  </repository>
</repositories>
]]></programlisting>
				<para>
					Or, you can add this information to your <code>~/.m2/settings.xml</code> file. For more information,
					see the <ulink url="&JBossMavenUsing;">JBoss wiki page</ulink>.
				</para>
			</sect3>
			<sect3 id="adding_modeshape_dependencies">
				<title>Add dependency to ModeShape</title>
				<para>
					Then, simply modify your project's POM by adding dependencies on the ModeShape JCR library:
			  </para>
<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<dependency>
  <groupId>org.modeshape</groupId>
  <artifactId>modeshape-jcr</artifactId>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
]]></programlisting>
				<para>
					This adds only the minimal libraries required to use ModeShape, so you need to add dependencies for 
					each of the connectors and sequencers you want to use. Here is the list of available sequencers:
				</para>
<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshape</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-sequencer-cnd</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshape</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-sequencer-ddl</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshapce</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-sequencer-images</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshape</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-sequencer-classfile</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshape</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-sequencer-java</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshape</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-sequencer-mp3</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshape</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-sequencer-msoffice</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshape</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-sequencer-xml</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshape</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-sequencer-text</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshape</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-sequencer-zip</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
]]></programlisting>
			<para>
				Here is the list of available connectors:
			</para>
<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshape</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-connector-filesystem</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshape</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-connector-infinispan</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshape</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-connector-jcr</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshape</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-connector-jbosscache</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshape</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-connector-jdbc-metadata</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshape</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-connector-store-jpa</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
  <groupid>org.modeshape</groupid>
  <artifactid>modeshape-connector-svn</artifactid>
  <version>2.0.0.Final</version>
</dependency>]]></programlisting>
	      <para>
		      The sequencer and connector libraries you choose, plus every third-party library they need, will be pulled in automatically 
		      by Maven into your project.
		    </para>
			</sect3>
		</sect2>
			<sect2 id="adding_logging_dependencies">
				<title>Add dependencies for logging</title>
				<para>
					ModeShape is designed to use the same logging framework as your application, and it uses SLF4J to accomplish this. 
					In other words, ModeShape depends upon the SLF4J API library, but requires you to provide provide a logging implementation 
					as well as the appropriate SLF4J binding JAR.
				</para>
				<para>
					For example, if your application is using <ulink url="&Log4J;">Log4J</ulink>, your application will already have a dependency 
					for it, and so ModeShape log messages will be sent to the same logging system used in your application, you need to add a 
					dependency to the SLF4J-to-Log4J binding JAR:
				</para>
<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[<dependency>
  <groupId>org.slf4j</groupId>
  <artifactId>slf4j-log4j12</artifactId>
  <version>1.5.11</version>
</dependency>
<dependency>
  <groupId>log4j</groupId>
  <artifactId>log4j</artifactId>
  <version>1.2.16</version>
</dependency>
]]></programlisting>
        <para>
	        Of course, SLF4J works with other logging frameworks, too. Some logging implementations (such as <ulink url="&LogBack;">LogBack</ulink>) 
	        implement the SLF4J API natively, meaning they require no binding JAR. For details on the options and how to configure them, see the 
	        <ulink url="&SLF4JManual;">SLF4J manual</ulink>.
        </para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="using_modeshape_via_jars">
			<title>Building against ModeShape via JARs</title>
			<para>
				If your application doesn't use Maven, you'll need to obtain the ModeShape JARs and place them onto your application's classpath. 
				ModeShape provides a <ulink url="&SingleDownload;">single download</ulink> with all of the JARs for all ModeShape components 
				and all dependencies. This file contains the following:
				<itemizedlist>
	        <listitem>
	          <para>
	            <emphasis role="strong"><code>modeshape-jcr-&versionNumber;-with-dependencies.jar</code></emphasis> contains the JARs 
							necessary to run the core ModeShape JCR repository engine, 
	            the in-memory connector, and the federating connector;
	          </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	          <para>
	            one <emphasis role="strong"><code>modeshape-connector-&lt;type>-&versionNumber;-with-dependencies.jar</code></emphasis> 
							for each type of connector, each containing the JARs necessary 
	            for that connector;
	          </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	          <para>
	            one <emphasis role="strong"><code>modeshape-sequencer-&lt;type>-&versionNumber;-with-dependencies.jar</code></emphasis> 
							for each type of sequencer, each containing the JARs necessary
	            for that sequencer;
	          </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	          <para>
	            <emphasis role="strong"><code>modeshape-mimetype-detector-aperture-&versionNumber;-with-dependencies.jar</code></emphasis> 
							contains all of the JARs required for the component that detects 
	            the MIME type of files based upon names and/or content; and
	          </para>
	        </listitem>
	        <listitem>
	          <para>
	            <emphasis role="strong"><code>modeshape-jpa-ddl-gen-&versionNumber;-jar-with-dependencies.jar</code></emphasis> 
							contains all of the JARs required to run the DDL generation utility.
	          </para>
	        </listitem>
	      </itemizedlist>
				Note that the core engine is required in all configurations. The <code>jcr-2.0.jar</code> file is not included and must be provided by you. 
				And, as mentioned in the <link linkend="adding_logging_dependencies">previous section</link>, ModeShape uses SLF4J for logging and you must provide 
				a logging implementation as well as the appropriate SLF4J binding JAR.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="using_modeshape_whats_next">
		<title>What's next</title>
		<para>
			This chapter outline how you configure ModeShape, how you then access a <code>javax.jcr.Repository</code> instance,
			and use the standard JCR API to interact with the repository. The
			<link linkend="downloading_and_building">next chapter </link> walks you through downloading
			and building the ModeShape examples, while <link linkend="sequencer_example">Chapter 5</link>
			and <link linkend="repository_example">Chapter 6</link> shows how to run the examples.
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
