<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ ModeShape (http://www.modeshape.org)
  ~
  ~ See the COPYRIGHT.txt file distributed with this work for information
  ~ regarding copyright ownership.  Some portions may be licensed
  ~ to Red Hat, Inc. under one or more contributor license agreements.
  ~ See the AUTHORS.txt file in the distribution for a full listing of 
  ~ individual contributors.
  ~
  ~ ModeShape is free software. Unless otherwise indicated, all code in ModeShape
  ~ is licensed to you under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as
  ~ published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of
  ~ the License, or (at your option) any later version.
  ~
  ~ ModeShape is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY
  ~ or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ for more details.
  ~
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ along with this distribution; if not, write to:
  ~ Free Software Foundation, Inc.
  ~ 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor
  ~ Boston, MA  02110-1301  USA
  -->
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"	[
<!ENTITY % CustomDTD SYSTEM "../../custom.dtd">
%CustomDTD;
]>
<chapter id="graph-model">
  <title>Graph Model</title>
  <para>
		One of the central concepts within ModeShape is that of its <emphasis>graph model</emphasis>.
		Information is structured into a hierarchy of nodes with properties, where nodes in the hierarchy
		are identified by their path (and/or identifier properties).  Properties are identified by
		a name that incorporates a namespace and local name, and contain one or more property values
		consisting of normal Java strings, names, paths, URIs, booleans, longs, doubles, decimals, binary content,
		dates, UUIDs, references to other nodes, or any other serializable object.
	</para>
	<para>
		This graph model is used throughout ModeShape: it forms the basis for the 
		<link linkend="connector_framework">connector framework</link>, it is used by the 
		<link linkend="sequencing_framework">sequencing framework</link> for the generated output,
		and it is what the <link linkend="jcr">JCR implementation</link> uses internally to access and operate
		on the repository content.
	</para>
	<para>
		Therefore, this chapter provides essential information that will be essential to really understanding
		how the connectors, sequencers, and other ModeShape features work.
	</para>
	<sect1 id="graph-names">
		<title>Names</title>
		<para>
			ModeShape uses names to identify quite a few different types of objects.  As we'll soon see, each property
			of a node is given by a name, and each segment in a path is comprised of a name.  Therefore,
			names are a very important concept.
		</para>
		<para>
			ModeShape names consist of a local part that is qualified with a namespace.  The local part can consist of
			any character, and the namespace is identified by a URI.  Namespaces were introduced in the
			<link linkend="execution-context">previous chapter</link> and are managed by the &ExecutionContext;'s
			<link linkend="namespace-registry">namespace registry</link>.  Namespaces help reduce the risk of
			clashes in names that have an equivalent same local part.
		</para>
		<para>
			All names are immutable, which means that once a &Name; object is created, it will never change.
			This characteristic makes it much easier to write thread-safe code - the objects never change and therefore
			require no locks or synchronization to guarantee atomic reads.  This is a technique that is more and more
			often found in newer languages and frameworks that simplify concurrent operations.
		</para>
		<para>
			&Name; is also a interface rather than a concrete class:
		</para>
<programlisting>
@Immutable
public interface &Name; extends Comparable&lt;&Name;>, &Serializable;, &Readable; {

    /**
     * Get the local name part of this qualified name.
     * @return the local name; never null
     */
    String getLocalName();

    /**
     * Get the URI for the namespace used in this qualified name.
     * @return the URI; never null but possibly empty
     */
    String getNamespaceUri();
}</programlisting>
		<para>
			This means that you need to use a factory to create &Name; instances.
		</para>
		<para>
			The use of a factory may seem like a disadvantage and unnecessary complexity, but there actually
			are several benefits.  First, it hides the concrete implementations, which is very appealing if
			an optimized implementation can be chosen for particular situations.  It also simplifies the
			usage, since &Name; only has a few methods.  Third, it allows the factory to cache or pool instances
			where appropriate to help conserve memory.  Finally, the very same factory actually serves as
			a <emphasis>conversion</emphasis> mechanism from other forms.  We'll actually see more of this
			later in this chapter, when we talk about other kinds of <link linkend="graph-properties">property values</link>.
		</para>
		<para>
			The factory for creating &Name; objects is called &NameFactory; and is available within the &ExecutionContext;, 
			via the <code>getValueFactories()</code> method.  
		</para>
		<para>
			We'll see how names are used later on, but one more point to make:  &Name; is both serializable and comparable,
			and all implementations should support <code>equals(...)</code> and <code>hashCode()</code> so that &Name; can
			be used as a key in a hash-based map.  &Name; also extends the &Readable; interface, which we'll learn
			more about later in this chapter.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="graph-paths">
		<title>Paths</title>
		<para>
			Another important concept in ModeShape's graph model is that of a <emphasis>path</emphasis>, which provides a way
			of locating a node within a hierarchy.  ModeShape's &Path; object is an immutable ordered sequence
			of &PathSegment; objects.  A small portion of the interface is shown here:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
@Immutable
public interface &Path; extends Comparable&lt;Path>, Iterable&lt;&PathSegment;>, &Serializable;, &Readable; {

    /**
     * Return the number of segments in this path.
     * @return the number of path segments
     */
    public int size();

    /**
     * Return whether this path represents the root path.
     * @return true if this path is the root path, or false otherwise
     */
    public boolean isRoot();

    /**
     * {@inheritDoc}
     */
    public Iterator&lt;&PathSegment;> iterator();

    /**
     * Obtain a copy of the segments in this path. None of the segments are encoded.
     * @return the array of segments as a copy
     */
    public &PathSegment;[] getSegmentsArray();

    /**
     * Get an unmodifiable list of the path segments.
     * @return the unmodifiable list of path segments; never null
     */
    public List&lt;&PathSegment;> getSegmentsList();
    /**
     * Get the last segment in this path.
     * @return the last segment, or null if the path is empty
     */
    public &PathSegment; getLastSegment();

    /**
     * Get the segment at the supplied index.
     * @param index the index
     * @return the segment
     * @throws IndexOutOfBoundsException if the index is out of bounds
     */
    public &PathSegment; getSegment( int index );

    /**
     * Return an iterator that walks the paths from the root path down to this path. This method 
     * always returns at least one path (the root returns an iterator containing itself).
     * @return the path iterator; never null
     */
    public Iterator&lt;&Path;> pathsFromRoot();

    /**
     * Return a new path consisting of the segments starting at <code>beginIndex</code> index (inclusive). 
     * This is equivalent to calling <code>path.subpath(beginIndex,path.size()-1)</code>.
     * @param beginIndex the beginning index, inclusive.
     * @return the specified subpath
     * @exception IndexOutOfBoundsException if the <code>beginIndex</code> is negative or larger 
     *            than the length of this <code>Path</code> object
     */
    public &Path; subpath( int beginIndex );

    /**
     * Return a new path consisting of the segments between the <code>beginIndex</code> index (inclusive)
     * and the <code>endIndex</code> index (exclusive).
     * @param beginIndex the beginning index, inclusive.
     * @param endIndex the ending index, exclusive.
     * @return the specified subpath
     * @exception IndexOutOfBoundsException if the <code>beginIndex</code> is negative, or 
     *            <code>endIndex</code> is larger than the length of this <code>Path</code> 
     *            object, or <code>beginIndex</code> is larger than <code>endIndex</code>.
     */
    public &Path; subpath( int beginIndex, int endIndex );

    ...
}   </programlisting>
		<para>
			There are actually quite a few methods (not shown above) for obtaining related paths: the path of the parent, the path of an ancestor,
			resolving a path relative to this path, normalizing a path (by removing "." and ".." segments), finding the lowest
			common ancestor shared with another path, etc. There are also a number of methods that compare the path with others,
			including determining whether a path is above, equal to, or below this path.
		</para>
		<para>
			Each &PathSegment; is an immutable pair of a &Name; and <emphasis>same-name-sibling (SNS) index</emphasis>.  When two sibling nodes
			have the same name, then the first sibling will have SNS index of "1" and the second will be given a SNS index of "2".
			(This mirrors the same-name-sibling index behavior of <ulink url="&JSR283;">JCR paths</ulink>.)
		</para>
		<programlisting>
@Immutable
public static interface &PathSegment; extends Cloneable, Comparable&lt;&PathSegment;>, &Serializable;, &Readable; 
{

    /**
     * Get the name component of this segment.
     * @return the segment's name
     */
    public &Name; getName();

    /**
     * Get the index for this segment, which will be 1 by default.
     * @return the index
     */
    public int getIndex();

    /**
     * Return whether this segment has an index that is not "1"
     * @return true if this segment has an index, or false otherwise.
     */
    public boolean hasIndex();

    /**
     * Return whether this segment is a self-reference (or ".").
     * @return true if the segment is a self-reference, or false otherwise.
     */
    public boolean isSelfReference();

    /**
     * Return whether this segment is a reference to a parent (or "..")
     * @return true if the segment is a parent-reference, or false otherwise.
     */
    public boolean isParentReference();
}
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			Like &Name;, the only way to create a &Path; or a &PathSegment; is to use the &PathFactory;, which is available 
			within the &ExecutionContext; via the <code>getValueFactories()</code> method.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="graph-properties">
		<title>Properties</title>
		<para>
			The ModeShape graph model allows nodes to hold multiple properties, where each property is identified
			by a unique &Name; and may have one or more values.  Like many of the other classes used in the graph model,
			&Property; is an immutable object that, once constructed, can never be changed and therefore provides
			a consistent snapshot of the state of a property as it existed at the time it was read.
		</para>
		<para>
		  ModeShape properties can hold a wide range of value objects, including normal Java strings, names, paths, 
		  URIs, booleans, longs, doubles, decimals, binary content,	dates, UUIDs, references to other nodes, 
		  or any other serializable object.  All but three of these are the standard Java classes: dates are
		  represented by an immutable &DateTime; class; binary content is represented by an immutable &Binary;
		  interface patterned after the interface of the same name in <ulink url="&JSR283;">JSR-283</ulink>;
		  and &Reference; is an immutable interface patterned after the corresponding interface is 
		  <ulink url="&JSR170;">JSR-170</ulink> and <ulink url="&JSR283;">JSR-283</ulink>.
		</para>
		<para>
			The &Property; interface defines methods for obtaining the name and property values:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
@Immutable
public interface &Property; extends Iterable&lt;Object>, Comparable&lt;&Property;>, &Readable; {

    /**
     * Get the name of the property.
     * 
     * @return the property name; never null
     */
    &Name; getName();

    /**
     * Get the number of actual values in this property.
     * @return the number of actual values in this property; always non-negative
     */
    int size();

    /**
     * Determine whether the property currently has multiple values.
     * @return true if the property has multiple values, or false otherwise.
     */
    boolean isMultiple();

    /**
     * Determine whether the property currently has a single value.
     * @return true if the property has a single value, or false otherwise.
     */
    boolean isSingle();

    /**
     * Determine whether this property has no actual values. This method may return <code>true</code> 
     * regardless of whether the property has a single value or multiple values.
     * This method is a convenience method that is equivalent to <code>size() == 0</code>.
     * @return true if this property has no values, or false otherwise
     */
    boolean isEmpty();

    /**
     * Obtain the property's first value in its natural form. This is equivalent to calling
     * <code>isEmpty() ? null : iterator().next()</code>
     * @return the first value, or null if the property is {@link #isEmpty() empty}
     */
    Object getFirstValue();

    /**
     * Obtain the property's values in their natural form. This is equivalent to calling <code>iterator()</code>.
     * A valid iterator is returned if the property has single valued or multi-valued.
     * The resulting iterator is immutable, and all property values are immutable.
     * @return an iterator over the values; never null
     */
    Iterator&lt;?> getValues();

    /**
     * Obtain the property's values as an array of objects in their natural form.
     * A valid iterator is returned if the property has single valued or multi-valued, or a
     * null value is returned if the property is {@link #isEmpty() empty}.
     * The resulting array is a copy, guaranteeing immutability for the property.
     * @return the array of values
     */
    Object[] getValuesAsArray();
}
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			Creating &Property; instances is done by using the &PropertyFactory; object owned by the &ExecutionContext;.
			This factory defines methods for creating properties with a &Name; and various representation of values,
			including variable-length arguments, arrays, &Iterator;, and &Iterable;.
		</para>
		<para>
			When it comes to using the property values, ModeShape takes a non-traditional approach.
			Many other graph models (including JCR) mark each property with a data type and then require 
			all property values adhere to this data type. When the property values are obtained, they
			are guaranteed to be of the correct type. However, many times the property's data type may
			not match the data type expected by the caller, and so a conversion may be required
			and thus has to be coded.
		</para>
		<para>
			The ModeShape graph model uses a different tact.  Because callers almost always have to convert the
			values to the types they can handle, ModeShape skips the steps of associating the  &Property; with a data type
			and ensuring the values match.  Instead, ModeShape simply provides a very easy mechanism to convert
			the property values to the type desired by the caller.  In fact, the conversion mechanism
			is exactly the same as the factories that create the values in the first place.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="graph-value-factories">
		<title>Values and Value Factories</title>
		<para>
			ModeShape properties can hold a variety of value object types: strings, names, paths, 
		  URIs, booleans, longs, doubles, decimals, binary content,	dates, UUIDs, references to other nodes, 
		  or any other serializable object.  To assist in the creation of these values and conversion
		  into other types, ModeShape defines a &ValueFactory; interface.  This interface is parameterized
		  with the type of value that is being created, but defines methods for creating those values
		  from all of the other known value types:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
public interface ValueFactory&lt;T> {

    /**
     * Get the &PropertyType; of values created by this factory.
     * @return the value type; never null
     */
    &PropertyType; getPropertyType();

		/*
		 * Methods to create a value by converting from another value type.
		 * If the supplied value is the same type as returned by this factory,
		 * these methods simply return the supplied value.
		 * All of these methods throw a &ValueFormatException; if the supplied value
		 * could not be converted to this type.
		 */
    T create( String value ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( String value, TextDecoder decoder ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( int value ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( long value ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( boolean value ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( float value ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( double value ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( &BigDecimal; value ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( &Calendar; value ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( &Date; value ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( &DateTime; value ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( &Name; value ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( &Path; value ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( &Reference; value ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( &URI; value ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( &UUID; value ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( byte[] value ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T create( &Binary; value ) throws ValueFormatException, IoException;
    T create( &InputStream; stream, long approximateLength ) throws ValueFormatException, IoException;
    T create( &Reader; reader, long approximateLength ) throws ValueFormatException, IoException;
    T create( Object value ) throws ValueFormatException, IoException;

    /*
     * Methods to create an array of values by converting from another array of values.
     * If the supplied values are the same type as returned by this factory,
     * these methods simply return the supplied array.
     * All of these methods throw a &ValueFormatException; if the supplied values
     * could not be converted to this type.
		 */
    T[] create( String[] values ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( String[] values, TextDecoder decoder ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( int[] values ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( long[] values ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( boolean[] values ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( float[] values ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( double[] values ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( &BigDecimal;[] values ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( &Calendar;[] values ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( &Date;[] values ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( &DateTime;[] values ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( &Name;[] values ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( &Path;[] values ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( &Reference;[] values ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( &URI;[] values ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( &UUID;[] values ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( byte[][] values ) throws ValueFormatException;
    T[] create( &Binary;[] values ) throws ValueFormatException, IoException;
    T[] create( Object[] values ) throws ValueFormatException, IoException;

    /**
     * Create an iterator over the values (of an unknown type). The factory converts any 
     * values as required.  This is useful when wanting to iterate over the values of a property,
     * where the resulting iterator exposes the desired type.
     * @param values the values
     * @return the iterator of type <code>T</code> over the values, or null if the supplied parameter is null
     * @throws &ValueFormatException; if the conversion from an iterator of objects could not be performed
     * @throws IoException If an unexpected problem occurs during the conversion.
     */
    Iterator&lt;T> create( &Iterator;&lt;?> values ) throws ValueFormatException, IoException;
    Iterable&lt;T> create( &Iterable;&lt;?> valueIterable ) throws ValueFormatException, IoException;
}
	</programlisting>
		<para>
			This makes it very easy to convert one or more values (of any type, including mixtures) into
			corresponding value(s) that are of the desired type.  For example, converting the first value
			of a property (regardless of type) to a String is simple:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
&ValueFactory;&lt;String> stringFactory = ...
&Property; property = ...
String value = stringFactory.create( property.getFirstValue() );
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			Likewise, iterating over the values in a property and converting them is just as easy:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
&ValueFactory;&lt;String> stringFactory = ...
&Property; property = ...
for ( String value : stringFactory.create(property) ) {
    // do something with the values
}
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			What we've glossed over so far, however, is how to obtain the correct &ValueFactory; for the desired type.
			If you remember back in the previous chapter, &ExecutionContext; has a <code>getValueFactories()</code> method
			that return a &ValueFactories; interface:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			This interface exposes a &ValueFactory; for each of the types, and even has methods to obtain a &ValueFactory;
			given the &PropertyType; enumeration.  So, the previous examples could be expanded a bit:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
&ValueFactory;&lt;String> stringFactory = context.getValueFactories().getStringFactory();
&Property; property = ...
String value = stringFactory.create( property.getFirstValue() );
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			and
		</para>
		<programlisting>
&ValueFactory;&lt;String> stringFactory = context.getValueFactories().getStringFactory();
&Property; property = ...
for ( String value : stringFactory.create(property) ) {
    // do something with the values
}
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			You might have noticed that several of the &ValueFactories; methods return subinterfaces of &ValueFactory;.  These
			add type-specific methods that are more commonly needed in certain cases.  For example, here is the &NameFactory; interface:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
public interface &NameFactory; extends &ValueFactory;&lt;&Name;> {

    &Name; create( String namespaceUri, String localName );
    &Name; create( String namespaceUri, String localName, TextDecoder decoder );

    &NamespaceRegistry; getNamespaceRegistry();
}
		</programlisting>
		<para>and here is the &DateTimeFactory; interface, which adds methods for creating &DateTime; values for the current
			time as well as for specific instants in time:</para>
		<programlisting>
public interface &DateTimeFactory; extends &ValueFactory;&lt;&DateTime;> {

    /**
     * Create a date-time instance for the current time in the local time zone.
     */
    &DateTime; create();

    /**
     * Create a date-time instance for the current time in UTC.
     */
    &DateTime; createUtc();

    &DateTime; create( &DateTime; original, long offsetInMillis );
    &DateTime; create( int year, int monthOfYear, int dayOfMonth,
                     int hourOfDay, int minuteOfHour, int secondOfMinute, int millisecondsOfSecond );
    &DateTime; create( int year, int monthOfYear, int dayOfMonth,
                     int hourOfDay, int minuteOfHour, int secondOfMinute, int millisecondsOfSecond,
                     int timeZoneOffsetHours );
    &DateTime; create(	int year, int monthOfYear, int dayOfMonth,
                     int hourOfDay, int minuteOfHour, int secondOfMinute, int millisecondsOfSecond,
                     int timeZoneOffsetHours, String timeZoneId );
}
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			The &PathFactory; interface defines methods for creating relative and absolute &Path; objects using combinations of other &Path; objects
			and &Name;s and &PathSegment;s,
			and introduces methods for creating &PathSegment; objects:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
public interface &PathFactory; extends &ValueFactory;&lt;&Path;> {

    &Path; createRootPath();
    &Path; createAbsolutePath( &Name;... segmentNames );
    &Path; createAbsolutePath( &PathSegment;... segments );
    &Path; createAbsolutePath( &Iterable;&lt;&PathSegment;> segments );

    &Path; createRelativePath();
    &Path; createRelativePath( &Name;... segmentNames );
    &Path; createRelativePath( &PathSegment;... segments );
    &Path; createRelativePath( &Iterable;&lt;&PathSegment;> segments );

    &Path; create( Path parentPath, &Path; childPath );
    &Path; create( Path parentPath, &Name; segmentName, int index );
    &Path; create( Path parentPath, String segmentName, int index );
    &Path; create( Path parentPath, &Name;... segmentNames );
    &Path; create( Path parentPath, &PathSegment;... segments );
    &Path; create( Path parentPath, &Iterable;&lt;&PathSegment;> segments );
    &Path; create( Path parentPath, String subpath );

    &PathSegment; createSegment( String segmentName );
    &PathSegment; createSegment( String segmentName, &TextDecoder; decoder );
    &PathSegment; createSegment( String segmentName, int index );
    &PathSegment; createSegment( &Name; segmentName );
    &PathSegment; createSegment( &Name; segmentName, int index );
}
</programlisting>
		<para>
			And finally, the &BinaryFactory; defines methods for creating &Binary; objects from a variety of binary formats,
			as well as a method that looks for a cached &Binary; instance given the supplied secure hash:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
public interface &BinaryFactory; extends &ValueFactory;&lt;&Binary;> {

    /**
     * Create a value from the binary content given by the supplied input, the approximate length, 
     * and the SHA-1 secure hash of the content. If the secure hash is null, then a secure hash is
     * computed from the content. If the secure hash is not null, it is assumed to be the hash for 
     * the content and may not be checked.
     */
    &Binary; create( &InputStream; stream, long approximateLength, byte[] secureHash ) 
                          throws ValueFormatException, IoException;
    &Binary; create( &Reader; reader, long approximateLength, byte[] secureHash ) 
                          throws ValueFormatException, IoException;

    /**
     * Create a binary value from the given file.
     */
    &Binary; create( &File; file ) throws ValueFormatException, IoException;

    /**
     * Find an existing binary value given the supplied secure hash. If no such binary value exists, 
     * null is returned. This method can be used when the caller knows the secure hash (e.g., from 
     * a previously-held &Binary; object), and would like to reuse an existing binary value 
     * (if possible) rather than recreate the binary value by processing the stream contents. This is
     * especially true when the size of the binary is quite large.
     * 
     * @param secureHash the secure hash of the binary content, which was probably obtained from a
     *        previously-held &Binary; object; a null or empty value is allowed, but will always 
     *        result in returning null
     * @return the existing Binary value that has the same secure hash, or null if there is no 
     *        such value available at this time
     */
    &Binary; find( byte[] secureHash );
}
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			ModeShape provides efficient implementations of all of these interfaces: the &ValueFactory; interfaces and subinterfaces;
			the &Path;, &PathSegment;, &Name;, &Binary;, &DateTime;, and &Reference; interfaces; and the &ValueFactories; interface
			returned by the &ExecutionContext;.  In fact, some of these interfaces have multiple implementations that are optimized for 
			specific but frequently-occurring conditions.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="graph-readable">
		<title>Readable, TextEncoder, and TextDecoder</title>
		<para>
			As shown above, the &Name;, &PathSegment;, &Path;, and &Property; interfaces all extend the &Readable; interface,
			which defines a number of <code>getString(...)</code> methods that can produce a (readable) string representation of
		  of that object.  Recall that all of these objects contain names with namespace URIs and local names (consisting of any
		  characters), and so obtaining a readable string representation will require converting the URIs to prefixes, 
		  escaping certain characters in the local names, and formatting the prefix and escaped local name appropriately.
		  The different <code>getString(...)</code> methods of the &Readable; interface accept various combinations
		  of &NamespaceRegistry; and &TextEncoder; parameters:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
@Immutable
public interface Readable {

    /**
     * Get the string form of the object. A default encoder is used to encode characters.
     * @return the encoded string
     */
    public String getString();

    /**
     * Get the encoded string form of the object, using the supplied encoder to encode characters.
     * @param encoder the encoder to use, or null if the default encoder should be used
     * @return the encoded string
     */
    public String getString( &TextEncoder; encoder );

    /**
     * Get the string form of the object, using the supplied namespace registry to convert any 
     * namespace URIs to prefixes. A default encoder is used to encode characters.
     * @param namespaceRegistry the namespace registry that should be used to obtain the prefix
     *        for any namespace URIs
     * @return the encoded string
     * @throws IllegalArgumentException if the namespace registry is null
     */
    public String getString( &NamespaceRegistry; namespaceRegistry );

    /**
     * Get the encoded string form of the object, using the supplied namespace registry to convert 
     * the any namespace URIs to prefixes.
     * @param namespaceRegistry the namespace registry that should be used to obtain the prefix for 
     *        the namespace URIs
     * @param encoder the encoder to use, or null if the default encoder should be used
     * @return the encoded string
     * @throws IllegalArgumentException if the namespace registry is null
     */
    public String getString( &NamespaceRegistry; namespaceRegistry,
                             &TextEncoder; encoder );

    /**
     * Get the encoded string form of the object, using the supplied namespace registry to convert 
     * the names' namespace URIs to prefixes and the supplied encoder to encode characters, and using 
     * the second delimiter to encode (or convert) the delimiter used between the namespace prefix 
     * and the local part of any names.
     * @param namespaceRegistry the namespace registry that should be used to obtain the prefix 
     *        for the namespace URIs in the names
     * @param encoder the encoder to use for encoding the local part and namespace prefix of any names, 
     *        or null if the default encoder should be used
     * @param delimiterEncoder the encoder to use for encoding the delimiter between the local part 
     *        and namespace prefix of any names, or null if the standard delimiter should be used
     * @return the encoded string
     */
    public String getString( &NamespaceRegistry; namespaceRegistry,
                             &TextEncoder; encoder, &TextEncoder; delimiterEncoder );
}
		</programlisting>
		<para>
			We've seen the &NamespaceRegistry; in the <link linkend="execution-context">previous chapter</link>,
			but we've haven't yet talked about the &TextEncoder; interface.  A &TextEncoder; merely does what
			you'd expect: it encodes the characters in a string using some implementation-specific algorithm.  
			ModeShape provides a number of &TextEncoder; implementations, including:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>The &Jsr283Encoder; escapes characters that are not allowed in JCR names, 
						per the <ulink url="&JSR283;">JSR-283</ulink> specification.  Specifically,
						these are the '*', '/', ':', '[', ']', and '|' characters, which are escaped by replacing
						them with the Unicode characters U+F02A, U+F02F, U+F03A, U+F05B, U+F05D, and U+F07C, respectively.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>The &NoOpEncoder; does no conversion.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>The &UrlEncoder; converts text to be used within the different parts of a URL, as defined by Section 2.3 of
						<ulink url="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2396.txt">RFC 2396</ulink>. Note that this class does not 
						encode a complete URL (since <code>java.net.URLEncoder</code> and <code>java.net.URLDecoder</code>
						should be used for such purposes).
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>The &XmlNameEncoder; converts any UTF-16 unicode character that is not a valid XML name character according to the 
						<ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml/#sec-common-syn">World Wide Web Consortium (W3C) Extensible Markup Language (XML) 1.0
						(Fourth Edition) Recommendation</ulink>, escaping such characters as <code>_xHHHH_</code>, where <code>HHHH</code> stands for the 
						four-digit hexadecimal UTF-16 unicode value for the character in the most significant bit first order. 
						For example, the name "Customer_ID" is encoded as "Customer_x0020_ID".
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>The &XmlValueEncoder; escapes characters that are not allowed in XML values.  Specifically,
						these are the '&amp;', '&lt;', '&gt;', '&quot;', and '&#039;', which are all escaped to
						"&amp;amp;", '&amp;lt;', '&amp;gt;', '&amp;quot;', and '&amp;#039;'.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>The &FileNameEncoder; escapes characters that are not allowed in file names on Linux, OS X, or Windows XP. 
						Unsafe characters are escaped as described in the &UrlEncoder;.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>The &SecureHashTextEncoder; performs a secure hash of the input text and returns that hash as the encoded text. 
						This encoder can be configured to use different secure hash algorithms and to return a fixed number of characters from the hash.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
			All of these classes also implement the &TextDecoder; interface, which defines a method that
			<emphasis>decodes</emphasis> an encoded string using the opposite transformation.
		</para>
		<para>
			Of course, you can provide alternative implementations, and supply them to the appropriate <code>getString(...)</code> methods
			as required.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="graph-location">
		<title>Locations</title>
		<para>
			In addition to &Path; objects, nodes can be identified by one or more <emphasis>identification properties</emphasis>.
			These really are just &Property; instances with names that have a special meaning 
			(usually to <link linkend="connector-framework">connectors</link>).
			ModeShape also defines a &Location; class that encapsulates:
		  <itemizedlist>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>the &Path; to the node; or</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>one or more <emphasis>identification properties</emphasis> that are likely source-specific
						and that are represented with &Property; objects; or</para>
		    </listitem>
		    <listitem>
		      <para>a combination of both.</para>
		    </listitem>
		  </itemizedlist>
			So, when a client knows the path and/or the identification properties, they can create a &Location; object
			and then use that to identify the node.  &Location; is a class that can be instantiated through factory 
			methods on the class:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
public abstract class &Location; implements &Iterable;&lt;&Property;>, Comparable&lt;&Location;> {

    public static &Location; create( &Path; path ) { ... }
    public static &Location; create( &UUID; uuid ) { ... }
    public static &Location; create( &Path; path, &UUID; uuid ) { ... }
    public static &Location; create( &Path; path, &Property; idProperty ) { ... }
    public static &Location; create( &Path; path, &Property; firstIdProperty, 
                                     &Property;... remainingIdProperties ) { ... }
    public static &Location; create( &Path; path, &Iterable;&lt;&Property; idProperties ) { ... }
    public static &Location; create( &Property; idProperty ) { ... }
    public static &Location; create( &Property; firstIdProperty, 
                                     &Property;... remainingIdProperties ) { ... }
    public static &Location; create( &Iterable;&lt;&Property;> idProperties ) { ... }
    public static &Location; create( &List;&lt;&Property;> idProperties ) { ... }
    ...
}		</programlisting>
		<para>
		  Like many of the other classes and interfaces, &Location; is immutable and cannot be changed once created.
		  However, there are methods on the class to create a copy of the &Location; object with a different &Path;,
		  a different &UUID;, or different identification properties:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
public abstract class &Location; implements &Iterable;&lt;&Property;>, Comparable&lt;&Location;> {
    ...
    public &Location; with( &Property; newIdProperty );
    public &Location; with( &Path; newPath );
    public &Location; with( &UUID; uuid );
    ...
}		</programlisting>
		<para>
			One more thing about locations: we'll see later in the next chapter how they are used to make requests
			to the <link linkend="connector-framework">connectors</link>.  When creating the requests, clients usually have an 
			incomplete location (e.g., a path but no identification properties).  When processing the requests, connectors
			provide an <emphasis>actual</emphasis> location that contains the path <emphasis>and</emphasis> all identification properties.
			If actual &Location; objects are then reused in subsequent requests by the client, the connectors will have the benefit of having
			both the path and identification properties and may be able to more efficiently locate the identified node.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="graph-api">
		<title>Graph API</title>
		<para>
			ModeShape's <emphasis>Graph API</emphasis> was designed as a lightweight public API for working with graph information.
			The &Graph; class is the primary class in API, and each instance represents a single, independent
			view of a single graph.  &Graph; instances don't maintain state, so every request (or batch of requests) operates against
			the underlying graph and then returns <emphasis>immutable snapshots</emphasis> of the requested state at the time
			the request was made.
		</para>
		<para>
			There are several ways to obtain a &Graph; instance, as we'll see in later chapters.  For the time being, the important
			thing to understand is what a &Graph; instance represents and how it interacts with the underlying content to return
			representations of portions of that underlying graph content.
		</para>
		<para>
			The &Graph; class basically represents an <ulink url="http://www.martinfowler.com/bliki/DomainSpecificLanguage.html">internal domain specific language (DSL)</ulink>,
			designed to be easy to use in an application.  
			The Graph API makes extensive use of interfaces and method chaining, so that methods return a concise interface that has only those
			methods that make sense at that point.  In fact, this should be really easy if your IDE has code completion.
			Just remember that under the covers, a &Graph; is just building &Request; objects, submitting them to the connector,
			and then exposing the results.
		</para>
		<para>
			The next few subsections describe how to use a &Graph; instance.
		</para>
		<sect2 id="graph-api-workspaces">
			<title>Using Workspaces</title>
		<para>
			ModeShape graphs have the notion of <emphasis>workspaces</emphasis> that provide different views of the content.  Some graphs may have
			one workspace, while others may have multiple workspaces.  Some graphs will allow a client to create new workspaces or destroy
			existing workspaces, while other graphs will not allow adding or removing workspaces.  Some graphs may have workspaces that may show the same (or very
			similar) content, while other graphs may have workspaces that contain completely independent content.
		</para>
		<para>
			The &Graph; object is always bound to a workspace, which initially is the <emphasis>default workspace</emphasis>.  To find out
			what the name of the default workspace is, simply ask for the current workspace after creating the &Graph;:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
&Workspace; current = graph.getCurrentWorkspace();
</programlisting>
		<para>
			To obtain the list of workspaces available in a graph, simply ask for them:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
&Set;&lt;&String;> workspaceNames = graph.getWorkspaces();
</programlisting>
		<para>Once you know the name of a particular workspace, you can specify that the graph should use it:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
graph.useWorkspace("myWorkspace");
</programlisting>
		<para>
			From this point forward, all requests will apply to the workspace named "myWorkspace".  At any time, you can use a different workspace,
			which will affect all subsequent requests made using the graph.  To go back to the default workspace, simply supply a null name:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
graph.useWorkspace(null);
</programlisting>
		<para>
			Of course, creating a new workspace is just as easy:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
graph.createWorkspace().named("newWorkspace");
</programlisting>
	  <para>This will attempt to create a workspace named "newWorkspace", which will fail if that workspace already exists.  You may
		want to create a new workspace with a name that should be altered if the name you supply is already used.  The following code shows
		how you can do this:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
graph.createWorkspace().namedSomethingLike("newWorkspace");
</programlisting>
	  <para>If there is no existing workspace named "newWorkspace", a new one will be created with this name.  However, if "newWorkspace" already
		exists, this call will create a workspace with a name that is some alteration of the supplied name.
		</para>
	  <para>
		You can also clone workspaces, too:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
graph.createWorkspace().clonedFrom("original").named("something");
</programlisting>
		<para>
			or
		</para>
		<programlisting>
graph.createWorkspace().clonedFrom("original").namedSomethingLike("something");
</programlisting>
		<para>
			As you can see, it's very easy to specify which workspace you want to use or to create new workspaces.  You can also find out which workspace
			the graph is currently using:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
&String; current = graph.getCurrentWorkspaceName();
</programlisting>
		<para>or, if you want, you can get more information about the workspace:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
&Workspace; current = graph.getCurrentWorkspace();
&String; name = current.getName();
&Location; rootLocation = current.getRoot();
</programlisting>
    </sect2>
		<sect2 id="graph_api_nodes">
			<title>Working with Nodes</title>
		<para>
			Now let's switch to working with nodes.  This first example returns a map of properties (keyed by property name) 
			for a node at a specific &Path;:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
&Path; path = ...
Map&lt;&Name;,&Property;> propertiesByName = graph.getPropertiesByName().on(path);
</programlisting>
		<para>
			This next example shows how the graph can be used to obtain and loop over the properties of a node:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
&Path; path = ...
for ( &Property; property : graph.getProperties().on(path) ) {
	  ...
}
</programlisting>
		<para>
			Likewise, the next example shows how the graph can be used to obtain and loop over the children of a node:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
&Path; path = ...
for ( &Location; child : graph.getChildren().of(path) ) {
    &Path; childPath = child.getPath();
	  ...
}
</programlisting>
		<para>
			Notice that the examples pass a &Path; instance to the <code>on(...)</code> and <code>of(...)</code> methods.  Many
			of the Graph API methods take a variety of parameter types, including String, &Path;s, &Location;s, &UUID;, or &Property; parameters.
			This should make it easy to use in many different situations.
		</para>
		<para>
			Of course, changing content is more interesting and offers more interesting possibilities.  Here are a few examples:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
&Path; path = ...
&Location; location = ...
&Property; idProp1 = ...
&Property; idProp2 = ...
&UUID; uuid = ...
graph.move(path).into(idProp1, idProp2);
graph.copy(path).into(location);
graph.delete(uuid);
graph.delete(idProp1,idProp2);
</programlisting>
		<para>
			The methods shown above work immediately, as soon as each request is built.  However, there is another way to use
			the &Graph; object, and that is in a <emphasis>batch</emphasis> mode.  Simply create a &GraphBatch; object using the
			<code>batch()</code> method, create the requests on that batch object, and then execute all of the commands on the
			batch by calling its <code>execute()</code> method.  That <code>execute()</code> method returns a &Results; interface
			that can be used to read the node information retrieved by the batched requests. 
		</para>
		<para>
			Method chaining works really well with the batch mode, since multiple commands can be assembled together very easily:
		</para>
		<programlisting>
&Path; path = ...
String path2 = ...
&Location; location = ...
&Property; idProp1 = ...
&Property; idProp2 = ...
&UUID; uuid = ...
graph.batch().move(path).into(idProp1, idProp2)
       .and().copy(path2).into(location)
       .and().delete(uuid)
       .execute();
&Results; results = graph.batch().read(path2)
                           .and().readChildren().of(idProp1,idProp2)
                           .and().readSugraphOfDepth(3).at(uuid2)
                           .execute();
for ( &Location; child : results.getNode(path2) ) {
    ...
}
</programlisting>
		<para>
			Of course, this section provided just a hint of the Graph API.  
			The &Graph; interface is actually quite complete and offers a full-featured approach for reading and updating a graph.
			For more information, see the &Graph; JavaDocs.
		</para>
	</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="graph-requests">
		<title>Requests</title>
		<para>
			ModeShape &Graph; objects operate upon the underlying graph content, but we haven't really talked about how that works.
			Recall that the &Graph; objects don't maintain any stateful representation of the content, but instead submit requests
			to the underlying graph and return representations of the requested portions of the content.
			This section focuses on what those requests look like, since they'll actually become very important when
			working with <link linkend="connector-framework">connectors</link> in the next chapter.
		</para>
		<para>
			A graph &Request; is an encapsulation of a command that is to be executed by the underlying graph owner (typically
			a connector).  Request objects can take many different forms, as there are different classes for each kind of request.
			Each request contains the information needed to complete the processing, and it also is the place
			where the results (or error) are recorded.
		</para>
		<para>
			The &Graph; object creates the &Request; objects using &Location; objects to identify the node (or nodes) that are the
			subject of the request.  The &Graph; can either submit the request immediately, or it can batch multiple requests
			together into "units of work".  The submitted requests are then processed by the underlying system (e.g., connector)
			and returned back to the &Graph; object, which then extracts and returns the results.
		</para>
		<para>
			There are actually quite a few different types of &Request; classes:
		</para>
		<table frame='all'>
			<title>Types of Read Requests</title>
			<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
	      <colspec colname='c1' colwidth="1*"/>
	      <colspec colname='c2' colwidth="1*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
			  		<entry>Name</entry>
			  		<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>ReadNodeRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to read a node's properties and children from the named workspace in the source.
							The node may be specified by path and/or by identification properties.
							The connector returns all properties and the locations for all children,
							or sets a &PathNotFoundException; error on the request if the node did not exist in the workspace.
							If the node is found, the connector sets on the request the actual location of the node (including the path and identification properties).
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the named workspace does not exist.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>VerifyNodeExistsRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to verify the existence of a node at the specified location in the named workspace of the source.
							The connector returns all the actual location for the node if it exists, or
							sets a &PathNotFoundException; error on the request if the node does not exist in the workspace.
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the named workspace does not exist.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ReadAllPropertiesRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to read all of the properties of a node from the named workspace in the source.
							The node may be specified by path and/or by identification properties.
							The connector returns all properties that were found on the node,
							or sets a &PathNotFoundException; error on the request if the node did not exist in the workspace.
							If the node is found, the connector sets on the request the actual location of the node (including the path and identification properties).
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the named workspace does not exist.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ReadPropertyRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to read  a single property of a node from the named workspace in the source.
							The node may be specified by path and/or by identification properties,
							and the property is specified by name.
							The connector returns the property if found on the node,
							or sets a &PathNotFoundException; error on the request if the node or property did not exist in the workspace.
							If the node is found, the connector sets on the request the actual location of the node (including the path and identification properties).
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the named workspace does not exist.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ReadAllChildrenRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to read all of the children of a node from the named workspace in the source.
							The node may be specified by path and/or by identification properties.
							The connector returns an ordered list of locations for each child found on the node,
							an empty list if the node had no children,
							or sets a &PathNotFoundException; error on the request if the node did not exist in the workspace.
							If the node is found, the connector sets on the request the actual location of the parent node (including the path and identification properties).
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the named workspace does not exist.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ReadBlockOfChildrenRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to read a block of children of a node, starting with the n<superscript>th</superscript> child from the named workspace in the source.
							This is designed to allow paging through the children, which is much more efficient for large numbers of children.
							The node may be specified by path and/or by identification properties, and the block
							is defined by a starting index and a count (i.e., the block size).
							The connector returns an ordered list of locations for each of the node's children found in the block,
							or an empty list if there are no children in that range.
							The connector also sets on the request the actual location of the parent node (including the path and identification properties)
							or sets a &PathNotFoundException; error on the request if the parent node did not exist in the workspace.
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the named workspace does not exist.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ReadNextBlockOfChildrenRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to read a block of children of a node, starting with the children that immediately follow
							a previously-returned child from the named workspace in the source.
							This is designed to allow paging through the children, which is much more efficient for large numbers of children.
							The node may be specified by path and/or by identification properties, and the block
							is defined by the location of the node immediately preceding the block and a count (i.e., the block size).
							The connector returns an ordered list of locations for each of the node's children found in the block,
							or an empty list if there are no children in that range.
							The connector also sets on the request the actual location of the parent node (including the path and identification properties)
							or sets a &PathNotFoundException; error on the request if the parent node did not exist in the workspace.
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the named workspace does not exist.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>ReadBranchRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to read a portion of a subgraph that has as its root a particular node, up to a maximum depth.
							This request is an efficient mechanism when a branch (or part of a branch) is to be navigated and processed,
							and replaces some non-trivial code to read the branch iteratively using multiple <code>ReadNodeRequest</code>s.
							The connector reads the branch to the specified maximum depth, returning the properties and children for all
							nodes found in the branch.  
							The connector also sets on the request the actual location of the branch's root node (including the path and identification properties).
							The connector sets a &PathNotFoundException; error on the request if the node at 
							the top of the branch does not exist in the workspace.
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the named workspace does not exist.
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<para>
		  &ChangeRequest; is a subclass of &Request; that provides a base class for all the requests that request a change
		  be made to the content.  As we'll see later, these &ChangeRequest; objects also get reused by the
		  <link linkend="graph-observation">observation</link> system.
		</para>
		<table frame='all'>
			<title>Types of Change Requests</title>
			<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
	      <colspec colname='c1' colwidth="1*"/>
	      <colspec colname='c2' colwidth="1*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
			  		<entry>Name</entry>
			  		<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>CreateNodeRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to create a node at the specified location and setting on the new node the properties included in the request.
							The connector creates the node at the desired location, adjusting any same-name-sibling indexes as required.
							(If an SNS index is provided in the new node's location, existing children with the same name after that SNS index
							will have their SNS indexes adjusted.  However, if the requested location does not include a SNS index, the new
							node is added after all existing children, and it's SNS index is set accordingly.)
							The connector also sets on the request the actual location of the new node (including the path and identification properties)..
							The connector sets a &PathNotFoundException; error on the request if the parent node does not exist in the workspace.
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the named workspace does not exist.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>RemovePropertiesRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to remove a set of properties on an existing node.  The request contains the location of the node as well as the
							names of the properties to be removed.  The connector performs these changes and sets on the request the
							actual location (including the path and identification properties) of the node.
							The connector sets a &PathNotFoundException; error on the request if the node does not exist in the workspace.
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the named workspace does not exist.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>UpdatePropertiesRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to set or update properties on an existing node.  The request contains the location of the node as well as the
							properties to be set and those to be deleted.  The connector performs these changes and sets on the request the
							actual location (including the path and identification properties) of the node.
							The connector sets a &PathNotFoundException; error on the request if the node does not exist in the workspace.
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the named workspace does not exist.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>RenameNodeRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to change the name of a node.  The connector changes the node's name, adjusts all SNS indexes
							accordingly, and returns the actual locations (including the path and identification properties) of both the original
							location and the new location.
							The connector sets a &PathNotFoundException; error on the request if the node does not exist in the workspace.
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the named workspace does not exist.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>CopyBranchRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to copy a portion of a subgraph that has as its root a particular node, up to a maximum depth.
							The request includes the name of the workspace where the original node is located as well as the name of the
							workspace where the copy is to be placed (these may be the same, but may be different).
							The connector copies the branch from the original location, up to the specified maximum depth, and places a copy
							of the node as a child of the new location.
							The connector also sets on the request the actual location (including the path and identification properties)
							of the original location as well as the location of the new copy.
							The connector sets a &PathNotFoundException; error on the request if the node at 
							the top of the branch does not exist in the workspace.
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if one of the named workspaces does not exist.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>MoveBranchRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to move a subgraph that has a particular node as its root.
							The connector moves the branch from the original location and places it as child of the specified new location.
							The connector also sets on the request the actual location (including the path and identification properties)
							of the original and new locations.  The connector will adjust SNS indexes accordingly.
							The connector sets a &PathNotFoundException; error on the request if the node that is to be moved or the
							new location do not exist in the workspace.
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the named workspace does not exist.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>DeleteBranchRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to delete an entire branch specified by a single node's location.
							The connector deletes the specified node and all nodes below it, and sets the actual location,
							including the path and identification properties, of the node that was deleted.
							The connector sets a &PathNotFoundException; error on the request if the node being deleted does not exist in the workspace.
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the named workspace does not exist.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>CompositeRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request that actually comprises multiple requests (none of which will be a composite).
							The connector simply processes all of the requests in the composite request, but should set on the composite
							request any error (usually the first error) that occurs during processing of the contained requests.
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<para>There are also requests that deal with workspaces:</para>
		<table frame='all'>
			<title>Types of Workspace Read Requests</title>
			<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
	      <colspec colname='c1' colwidth="1*"/>
	      <colspec colname='c2' colwidth="1*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
			  		<entry>Name</entry>
			  		<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>GetWorkspacesRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to obtain the names of the existing workspaces that are accessible to the caller.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>VerifyWorkspaceRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to verify that a workspace with a particular name exists.
							The connector returns the actual location for the root node if the workspace exists, as well as the actual name of the workspace
							(e.g., the default workspace name if a null name is supplied).
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<para>And there are also requests that deal with changing workspaces (and thus extend &ChangeRequest;):</para>
		<table frame='all'>
			<title>Types of Workspace Change Requests</title>
			<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
	      <colspec colname='c1' colwidth="1*"/>
	      <colspec colname='c2' colwidth="1*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
			  		<entry>Name</entry>
			  		<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>CreateWorkspaceRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to create a workspace with a particular name.
							The connector returns the actual location for the root node if the workspace exists, as well as the actual name of the workspace
							(e.g., the default workspace name if a null name is supplied).
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the named workspace already exists.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>DestroyWorkspaceRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to destroy a workspace with a particular name.
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the named workspace does not exist.
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>CloneWorkspaceRequest</entry>
						<entry>
							A request to clone one named workspace as another new named workspace.
							The connector sets a &InvalidWorkspaceException; error on the request if the original workspace does not exist, 
							or if the new workspace already exists.
						</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
    <para>
			Although there are over a dozen different kinds of requests, we do anticipate adding more in future releases.
			For example, ModeShape has recently added support for searching repository content in sources through an additional subclass of &Request;.
			Getting the version history for a node will likely be another kind of request added in an upcoming release.
		</para>
		<para>
			This section covered the different kinds of &Request; classes.  The next section provides a easy way to encapsulate how
			a component should responds to these requests, and after that we'll see how these &Request; objects are also used
			in the <link linkend="graph-observation">observation</link> framework.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="graph-request-processors">
		<title>Request processors</title>
		<para>
			ModeShape connectors are typically the components that receive these &Request; objects.  We'll dive deep into connectors
			in the <link linkend="connector-framework">next chapter</link>, but before we do there is one more component related to
			&Request;s that should be discussed.
		</para>
		<para>
			The &RequestProcessor; class is an abstract class that defines a <code>process(...)</code> method for each concrete &Request; subclass.
			In other words, there is a <code>process(CompositeRequest)</code> method, a <code>process(ReadNodeRequest)</code> method,
			and so on. This makes it easy to implement behavior that responds to the different kinds of &Request; classes:
			simply subclass the &RequestProcessor;, override all of the abstract methods, and optionally
			overriding any of the other methods that have a default implementation.
		</para>
		<note>
			<para>
				The &RequestProcessor; abstract class contains default implementations for quite a few of the <code>process(...)</code> methods,
				and these will be <emphasis>sufficient</emphasis>	but probably not efficient or optimum.  If you can provide a more efficient
				implementation given your source, feel free to do so.  However, if performance is not a big issue, all of the concrete methods
				will provide the correct behavior. Keep things simple to start out - you can always provide better implementations later.
			</para>
		</note>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="graph-observation">
		<title>Observation</title>
		<para>
			The ModeShape graph model also incorporates an observation framework that allows components to register and
			be notified when changes occur within the content owned by a graph.
		</para>
		<para>
			Many event frameworks define the listeners and sources as interfaces.  While this is often useful, it requires
			that the implementations properly address the thread-safe semantics of managing and calling the listeners.
			The ModeShape observation framework uses abstract or concrete classes to minimize the effort required for implementing
			&ChangeObserver; or &Observable;. These abstract classes provide implementations for a number of
			utility methods (such as the <code>unregister()</code> method on &ChangeObserver;) that
			also save effort and code.
		</para>
		<para>
			However, one of the more important reasons for providing classes is that &ChangeObserver; uses 
			weak references to track the &Observable; instances, and the &ChangeObservers;
			class uses weak references for the listeners.  This means that an observer does not prevent &Observable; instances
			from being garbage collected, nor do observers prevent &Observable; instances from being garbage collected.
			These abstract class provide all this functionality for free.
		</para>
		<sect2 id="graph-observable">
			<title>Observable</title>
			<para>
				Any component that can have changes and be observed can implement the &Observable; interface.  This interface
				allows &Observer;s to register (or be registered) to receive notifications of the changes.  However, a concrete and thread-safe 
				implementation of this interface, called &ChangeObservers;, is available and should be used where possible, since it 
				automatically manages the registered &ChangeObserver; instances and properly implements the register and unregister mechanisms.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="graph-observers">
			<title>Observers</title>
			<para>
				Components that are to recieve notifications of changes are called <emphasis>observers</emphasis>.  To create an observer, simply extend 
				the &ChangeObserver; abstract class and provide an implementation of the <code>notify(&Changes;)</code> method.
				Then, register the observer with an &Observable; using its <code>register(&ChangeObserver;)</code> method.
				The observer's <code>notify(&Changes;)</code> method will then be called with the changes that have
				been made to the &Observable;.
			</para>
			<para>
				When an observer is no longer needed, it should be unregistered from all &Observable; instances with which
				it was registered.  The &ChangeObserver; class automatically tracks which &Observable; instances it is
				registered with, and calling the observer's <code>unregister()</code> will unregister the observer from
				all of these &Observable;s.  Alternatively, an observer can be unregistered from a single &Observable; using the
				&Observable;'s <code>unregister(&ChangeObserver;)</code> method.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="graph-changes">
			<title>Changes</title>
			<para>
				The &Changes; class represents the set of individual changes that have been made during a single, atomic
				operation.  Each &Changes; instance has information about the source of the changes, the timestamp at which
				the changes occurred, and the individual changes that were made.  These individual changes take the form of
				&ChangeRequest; objects, which we'll see more of in the next chapter.  Each request is 
				frozen, meaning it is immutable and will not change.  Also none of the change requests will be marked as cancelled.
			</para>
			<para>
				Using the actual &ChangeRequest; objects as the "events" has a number of advantages.
				First, the existing &ChangeRequest; subclasses already contain the information to accurately and completely
				describe the operation.  Reusing these classes means we don't need a duplicate class structure or come up with a generic
				event class.
			</para>
			<para>
				Second, the requests have all the state required for an event, plus they often will have more.  For example,
				the &DeleteBranchRequest; has the actual location of the branch that was deleted (and in this way is not much different than
				a more generic event), but the &CreateNodeRequest; has the actual location of the created node along with the properties
				of that node.  Additionally, the &RemovePropertyRequest; has the actual location of the node along with the name of the property
				that was removed.  In many cases, these requests have all the information a more general event class might have but
				then hopefully enough information for many observers to use directly without having to read the graph to decide what
				actually changed. 
			</para>
			<para>
				Third, the requests that make up a &Changes; instance can actually be replayed.  Consider the case of a cache
				that is backed by a &RepositorySource;, which might use an observer to keep the cache in sync.  
				As the cache is notified of &Changes;, the cache can simply replay the changes against its source.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<para>
			As we'll see in the <link linkend="connector-framework">next chapter</link>, each connector is responsible for propagating
			the &ChangeRequest; objects to the connector's &Observer;.  But that's not the only use of &Observer;s.
			We'll also see later how the <link linkend="sequencing-framework">sequencing system</link> uses &Observer;s to monitor
			for changes in the graph content to determine which, if any, sequencers should be run.  And, the
			<link linkend="jcr">JCR implementation</link> also uses the observation framework to propagate those changes
			to JCR clients.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<para>
			In this chapter, we introduced ModeShape's <emphasis>graph model</emphasis> and showed the different
			kinds of objects used to represent nodes, paths, names, and properties.  We saw how all of these objects
			are actually immutable, and how the low-level Graph API uses this characteristic to provide a stateless
			and thread-safe interface for working with repository content using the <emphasis>request model</emphasis>
			used to read, update, and change content.
		</para>
		<para>
			Next, we'll dive into the <link linkend="connector_framework">connector framework</link>, which builds
			on top of the graph model and request model, allowing ModeShape to access the graph content stored
			in many different kinds of systems.
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
