<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ~ JBoss DNA (http://www.jboss.org/dna)
  ~
  ~ See the COPYRIGHT.txt file distributed with this work for information
  ~ regarding copyright ownership.  Some portions may be licensed
  ~ to Red Hat, Inc. under one or more contributor license agreements.
  ~ See the AUTHORS.txt file in the distribution for a full listing of 
  ~ individual contributors.
  ~
  ~ JBoss DNA is free software. Unless otherwise indicated, all code in JBoss DNA
  ~ is licensed to you under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as
  ~ published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of
  ~ the License, or (at your option) any later version.
  ~
  ~ JBoss DNA is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
  ~ but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY
  ~ or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ for more details.
  ~
  ~ You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public License
  ~ along with this distribution; if not, write to:
  ~ Free Software Foundation, Inc.
  ~ 51 Franklin Street, Fifth Floor
  ~ Boston, MA  02110-1301  USA
  -->
<!DOCTYPE preface PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd"	[
<!ENTITY % CustomDTD SYSTEM "../../custom.dtd">
%CustomDTD;
]>
<chapter id="development-tools">
  <title>Developer tools</title>
  <para>
		The JBoss DNA project uses <link linkend="maven">Maven</link> as its primary build tool, <link linkend="svn">Subversion</link>
		for its source code repository, <link linkend="jira">JIRA</link> for the issue management and bug tracking system,
		and <link linkend="hudson">Hudson</link> for the continuous integration system.  We do not stipulate a specific integrated
		development environment (IDE), although most of us use <link linkend="eclipse">Eclipse</link> and rely upon the code formatting
		and compile preferences to ensure no warnings or errors.
  </para>
	<para>
		The rest of this chapter talks in more detail about these different tools and how to set them up. But first, we briefly describe
		our approach to development.
	</para>
  <sect1 id="methodology">
    <title>Development methodology</title>
    <para>
			Rather than use a single formal development methodology, the JBoss DNA project incorporates those techniques, activities, and 
			processes that are practical and work for the project. In fact, the committers are given a lot of freedom for how they develop 
			the components and features they work on.
		</para>
		<para>
			Nevertheless, we do encourage familiarity with several major techniques, including:
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="strong"><ulink url="&Wikipedia;Agile_software_development">Agile software development</ulink></emphasis>
					  includes those software methodologies (e.g., Scrum) that promote development iterations and open collaboration.  While the
						JBoss DNA project doesn't follow these closely, we do emphasize the importance of always having running software
						and using running software as a measure of progress.  The JBoss DNA project also wants to move to more frequent
						releases (on the order of 4-6 weeks)
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="strong"><ulink url="&Wikipedia;Test-driven_development">Test-driven development (TDD)</ulink></emphasis>
						techniques encourage first writing test cases for new features and functionality, then changing the code to add the
						new features and functionality, and finally the code is refactored to clean-up and address any duplication or inconsistencies.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="strong"><ulink url="http://behaviour-driven.org/">Behavior-driven development (BDD)</ulink></emphasis>
						is an evolution of TDD, where developers specify the desired behaviors first (rather than writing "tests").
						In reality, this BDD adopts the language of the user so that tests are written using words that are meaningful
						to users.  With recent test frameworks (like JUnit 4.4), we're able to write our unit tests to express
						the desired behavior.  For example, a test class for sequencer implementation might have a test method
						<code>shouldNotThrowAnErrorWhenStreamIsNull()</code>, which is very easy to understand the intent.
						The result appears to be a larger number of finer-grained test methods, but which are more easily understood
						and easier to write.  In fact, many advocates of BDD argue that one of the biggest challenges of TDD is knowing what
						tests to write in the beginning, whereas with BDD the shift in focus and terminology make it easier for more
						developers to enumerate the tests they need.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						<emphasis role="strong"><ulink url="&Wikipedia;Lean_software_development">Lean software development</ulink></emphasis>
						is an adaptation of <ulink url="&Wikipedia;Lean_manufacturing">lean manufacturing techniques</ulink>,
						where emphasis is placed on eliminating waste (e.g., defects, unnecessary complexity, unnecessary code/functionality/features), 
						delivering as fast as possible, deferring irrevocable decisions as much as possible,
						continuous learning (continuously adapting and improving the process), empowering the team (or community, in our case),
						and several other guidelines.  Lean software development can be thought of as an evolution of agile techniques
						in the same way that behavior-driven development is an evolution of test-driven development.  Lean techniques
						help the developer to recognize and understand how and why features, bugs, and even their processes impact the development
						of software.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
    </para>
  </sect1>
	<sect1 id="jdk">
		<title>JDK</title>
		<para>
			Currently, JBoss DNA is developed and built using <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/index_jdk5.jsp">JDK 5</ulink>.
			So if you're trying to get JBoss DNA to compile locally, you should make sure you have the JDK 5 installed and are using it.
			If you're a contributor, you should make sure that you're using JDK 5 before committing any changes.  
		</para>
		<note>
			<para>
				You should be able to use the <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/index.jsp">latest JDK</ulink>,
				which is currently JDK 6.  It is possible to build JBoss DNA using JDK 6 without any code changes, but it's 
				not our official JDK (yet).
			</para>
			<para>
				Why do we build using JDK 5 and not 6? The main reason is that if we were to use JDK 6, then JBoss DNA couldn't really be used in any
				applications or projects that still used JDK 5.  Plus, anybody using JDK 6 can still use JBoss DNA.
				However, considering that the end-of-life for Java 5 is 
				<ulink url="http://java.sun.com/products/archive/eol.policy.html">October 2009</ulink>, we will likely be switching to 
				Java 6 sometime in 2010.
			</para>
		</note>
		<para>
			When installing a JDK, simply follow the procedure for your particular platform.  On most platforms, this should set the
			<code>JAVA_HOME</code> environment variable.  But if you run into any problems, first check that this environment
			variable was set to the correct location, and then check that you're running the version you expect by running
			the following command:
		</para>
		<programlisting>$ java -version</programlisting>
		<para>
			If you don't see the correct version, double-check your JDK installation.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="jira">
		<title>JIRA</title>
		<para>
			JBoss DNA uses <ulink url="&JIRA;">JIRA</ulink> as its bug tracking, issue tracking, and project management tool.
			This is a browser-based tool, with very good functionality for managing the different tasks.  It also serves as
			the community's roadmap, since we can define new features and manage them along side the bugs and other issues.
			Although most of the issues have been created by community members, we encourage any users to suggest new features,
			log defects, or identify shortcomings in JBoss DNA.
		</para>
		<para>
			The JBoss DNA community also encourages its members to work only issues that are managed in JIRA, and preferably those
			that are targeted to the current release effort.  If something isn't in JIRA but needs to get done, then create an 
			issue before you start working on the code changes.  Once you have code changes, you can upload a patch to the JIRA issue
			if the change is complex, if you want someone to review it, or if you don't have commit privileges and have fixed
			a bug.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="svn">
		<title>Subversion</title>
		<para>JBoss DNA uses Subversion as its source code management system, and specifically the instance at 
			<ulink url="http://www.jboss.org">JBoss.org</ulink>.  Although you can view the
			<ulink url="&Subversion;trunk/">trunk</ulink> of the Subversion repository directly
			(or using <ulink url="&Fisheye;trunk">FishEye</ulink>) through your browser,
			in order to get more than just a few files of the latest version of the source code, you probably want
		 	to have an SVN client installed.  Several IDE's have SVN support included (or available as plugins),
			but having the command-line SVN client is recommended.  See 
			<ulink url="http://subversion.tigris.org/">http://subversion.tigris.org/</ulink> for downloads and instructions for your
			particular platform.
		</para>
		<para>
			Here are some useful URLs for the JBoss DNA Subversion:
		</para>
		<table frame='all'>
			<title>SVN URLs for JBoss DNA</title>
			<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
	      <colspec colname='c1' colwidth="1*"/>
	      <colspec colname='c2' colwidth="1*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
			  		<entry>Repository</entry>
			  		<entry>URL</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Anonymous Access URL</entry>
						<entry><ulink url="&Subversion;trunk/">&Subversion;trunk/</ulink></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Secure Developer Access URL</entry>
						<entry><ulink url="&Fisheye;trunk/">&Fisheye;trunk/</ulink></entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>FishEye Code Browser</entry>
						<entry><ulink url="&SecureSubversion;trunk/">&SecureSubversion;trunk/</ulink></entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<para>
			When committing to SVN, be sure to include in a commit comment that includes the JIRA issue that the commit applies to and a very
			good and thorough description of what was done.  It only takes a minute or two to be very clear about the change.  And including
			the JIRA issue (e.g., "DNA-123") in the comment allows the JIRA system to track the changes that have been made for each issue.
		</para>
		<para>
			Also, any single SVN commit should apply to one and only one JIRA issue.  Doing this helps ensure that each commit is atomic
			and focused on a single activity.  There are exceptions to this rule, but they are rare.
		</para>
		<para>
			Sometimes you may have some local changes that you don't want to (or aren't allowed to) commit.  You can make a patch file
			and upload it to the JIRA issue, allowing other committers to review the patch.  However, to ensure that patches are easily
			applied, please use SVN to create the patch.  To do this, simply do the following in the top of the codebase (e.g., the 
			<code>trunk</code> directory):
		</para>
		<programlisting>$ svn diff . > ~/DNA-000.patch</programlisting> 
		<para>
			where <code>DNA-000</code> represents the DNA issue number.  Note that the above command places the patch file in your home directory,
			but you can place the patch file anywhere.  Then, simply use JIRA to attach the patch file to the particular issue, also adding
			a comment that describes the version number against which the patch was created.
		</para>
		<para>
			To apply a patch, you usually want to start with a workspace that has no changes.  Download the patch file, then issue the
			following command (again, from the top-level of the workspace):
		</para>
		<programlisting>$ patch -E -p0 &lt; ~/DNA-000.patch</programlisting> 
		<para>
			The "-E" option specifies to delete any files that were made empty by the application of the patch, and the "-p0" option instructs
			the patch tool to not change any of the paths.  After you run this command, your working area should have the changes defined
			by the patch.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="git">
		<title>Git</title>
		<para>
			Several contributors are using <ulink url="&Git;">Git</ulink> on their local development machines.  This allows
			the developer to use Git branches, commits, merges, and other Git tools, but still using 
			the JBoss DNA <link linkend="svn">Subversion</link> repository.  For more information, see our 
			<ulink url="http://jbossdna.blogspot.com/2009/05/git-and-svn-beginning.html">blog</ulink>
			<ulink url="http://jbossdna.blogspot.com/2009/05/git-it-together-with-subversion.html">posts</ulink> on the topic.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="maven">
		<title>Maven</title>
		<para>JBoss DNA uses Maven 2 for its build system, as is this example. Using Maven 2 has several advantages, including
	    the ability to manage dependencies. If a library is needed, Maven automatically finds and downloads that library, plus
	    everything that library needs. This means that it's very easy to build the examples - or even create a maven project that
	    depends on the JBoss DNA JARs.</para>
		<para>
      To use Maven with JBoss DNA, you'll need to have <link linkend="jdk">JDK 5 or 6</link> and Maven 2.0.9 (or higher).</para>
		<para>
      Maven can be downloaded from <ulink url="http://maven.apache.org/">http://maven.apache.org/</ulink>, and is installed by unzipping the
      <code>maven-2.0.9-bin.zip</code> file to a convenient location on your local disk. Simply add <code>$MAVEN_HOME/bin</code>
      to your path and add the following profile to your <code>~/.m2/settings.xml</code> file:
		</para>
		<programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[
<settings>
  <profiles>
    <profile>
      <id>jboss.repository</id>
      <activation>
        <property>
          <name>!jboss.repository.off</name>
        </property>
      </activation>
      <repositories>
        <repository>
          <id>snapshots.jboss.org</id>
          <url>http://snapshots.jboss.org/maven2</url>
          <snapshots>
            <enabled>true</enabled>
          </snapshots>
        </repository>
        <repository>
          <id>repository.jboss.org</id>
          <url>http://repository.jboss.org/maven2</url>
          <snapshots>
            <enabled>false</enabled>
          </snapshots>
        </repository>
      </repositories>
      <pluginRepositories>
        <pluginRepository>
          <id>repository.jboss.org</id>
          <url>http://repository.jboss.org/maven2</url>
          <snapshots>
            <enabled>false</enabled>
          </snapshots>
        </pluginRepository>
        <pluginRepository>
          <id>snapshots.jboss.org</id>
          <url>http://snapshots.jboss.org/maven2</url>
          <snapshots>
            <enabled>true</enabled>
          </snapshots>
        </pluginRepository>
      </pluginRepositories>
    </profile>
  </profiles>
</settings>
]]></programlisting>
		<para>This profile informs Maven of the two JBoss repositories (<ulink url="http://repository.jboss.org/maven2">snapshots</ulink> 
		  and <ulink url="http://snapshots.jboss.org/maven2">releases</ulink>) that contain all of the JARs for JBoss DNA and all dependent libraries.
		</para>
		<para>While you're adding <code>$MAVEN_HOME/bin</code> to your path, you should also set the <code>$MAVEN_OPTS</code> environment variable
		  to "<code>-Xmx256m</code>".  If you don't do this, you'll likely see an <code>java.lang.OutOfMemoryError</code> sometime during a full
		  build.
		</para>
		<note>
			<para>
				The JBoss Maven repository provides a central location for not only the artifacts produced by the JBoss.org projects (well, at least those
				that use Maven), but also is where those projects can place the artifacts that they depend on.  JBoss DNA has a policy that
				the <emphasis>source code and JARs</emphasis> for <emphasis>all</emphasis> dependencies <emphasis>must</emphasis> be loaded into the 
				JBoss Maven repository.  It may be a little bit more work for the developers, but it does help ensure that developers have easy
				access to the source and that the project (and dependencies) can always be rebuilt when needed.
			</para>
			<para>
				For more information about the JBoss Maven repository, including instructions for adding source and JAR artifacts, 
				see the <ulink url="http://wiki.jboss.org/wiki/Maven">JBoss.org Wiki</ulink>.
			</para>
		</note>
		<sect2 id="build_commands">
			<title>Building</title>
			<para>
				There are just a few commands that are useful for building JBoss DNA (and it's <link linkend="modules">subprojects</link>).
				Usually, these are issued while at the top level of the code (usually just below <code>trunk/</code>), although issuing
				them inside a subproject just applies to that subproject.
			</para>
			<table frame='all'>
				<title>Useful Maven commands</title>
				<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
		      <colspec colname='c1' colwidth="1*"/>
		      <colspec colname='c2' colwidth="1*"/>
					<thead>
						<row>
				  		<entry>Command</entry>
				  		<entry>Description</entry>
						</row>
					</thead>
					<tbody>
						<row>
							<entry><code>mvn clean</code></entry>
							<entry>Clean up all built artifacts (e.g., the <code>target/</code> directory in each project)</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><code>mvn clean install</code></entry>
							<entry>Called the "quick build".  Clean up all produced artifacts; compile the source code and test cases; 
								run all of the unit tests; and install the resulting JAR artifact(s)
								into your local Maven repository (e.g, usually <code>~/.m2/repository</code>).  This is often what
								developers run prior to checking in changes, since it generally runs quickly.
								Note that no integration tests are performed, and HSQLDB is used when a database is needed.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><code>mvn clean install -Ddatabase=dbprofile</code></entry>
							<entry>Same as the "quick build", except that it specifies the database management system
								that is to be used by the tests.
								Options for "<code>dbprofile</code>" values are: 
								"<code>hsqldb</code>", "<code>h2</code>", 
								"<code>postgresql_local</code>", "<code>postgresql8</code>",
								"<code>mysql5</code>", 
								"<code>oracle9i</code>", "<code>oracle10g</code>", "<code>oracle11g</code>", 
								"<code>db2v8</code>", "<code>db2v9</code>", 
								"<code>sybase15</code>", and 
								"<code>mssql2005</code>".
								The database connection information for these database profiles are in the parent "pom.xml" file,
								and most of these are configured to use database instances within the JBoss Quality Assurance
								lab and are accessible only to Red Hat employees.  However, feel free to add your own profiles
								or even change the settings in the POM file to suit your needs.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><code>mvn -P integration clean install</code></entry>
							<entry>This "integration build" does everything the "quick" build does plus it compiles and
								runs the integration tests, which take several extra minutes to run.
							  Also, HSQLDB is used when a database is needed.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><code>mvn -P integration clean install -Ddatabase=dbprofile</code></entry>
							<entry>This does the same as the "integration build", except that it specifies the database management system
								that is to be used by the unit and integration tests.  Options for the "<code>dbprofile</code>" values are
								the same as listed above.
							</entry>
						</row>
						<row>
							<entry><code>mvn -P assembly clean install</code></entry>
							<entry>This runs a builds all source code, documentation, JavaDoc, runs all unit and integration tests,
								and produces all assemblies (e.g., zip files).
							  HSQLDB is used when a database is needed.
							</entry>
						</row>
					</tbody>
				</tgroup>
			</table>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="hudson">
		<title>Continuous integration with Hudson</title>
		<para>JBoss DNA's continuous integration is done with several Hudson jobs on <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org">JBoss.org</ulink>.
		  These jobs run periodically and basically run the Maven build process.  Any build failures or test failures are reported,
		  as are basic statistics and history for each job.
		</para>
		<table frame='all'>
			<title>Continuous integration jobs</title>
			<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
	      <colspec colname='c1' colwidth="1*"/>
	      <colspec colname='c2' colwidth="1*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
			  		<entry>Job</entry>
			  		<entry>Description</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry><ulink url="http://hudson.jboss.org/hudson/job/DNA%20continuous%20on%20JDK1.5/">Continuous on JDK 5</ulink></entry>
						<entry>Continuous build that runs an integration build after changes are committed to SVN.  SVN is polled every 15 minutes.</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry><ulink url="http://hudson.jboss.org/hudson/job/DNA%20nightly%20integration%20on%20JDK1.5/">Nightly on JDK 5</ulink></entry>
						<entry>Integration build that runs every night (usually around 2 a.m. EDT), regardless of whether changes have been committed to SVN
							since the previous night.</entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="eclipse">
		<title>Eclipse IDE</title>
		<para>Many of the JBoss DNA committers use the Eclipse IDE, and all project files required by Eclipse are committed in SVN, making
			it pretty easy to get an Eclipse workspace running with all of the JBoss DNA projects.
		</para>
		<para>We're using the latest released version of Eclipse, 
			available from <ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org/">Eclipse.org</ulink>.  Simply follow the instructions for your platform.
		</para>
		<para>
			After Eclipse is installed, create a new workspace.  Before importing the JBoss DNA projects, import (via 
			<emphasis role="strong">File->Import->Preferences</emphasis>) the subset of the Eclipse preferences by importing the 
			<code>eclipse-preferences.epf</code> file (located under <code>trunk</code>). Then, open the Eclipse preferences and 
			open the <emphasis role="strong">Java->Code Style-> Formatter</emphasis> preference page, and press the "Import" button and
			choose the <code>eclipse-code-formatter-profile.xml</code> file (also located under <code>trunk</code>).  This will load the code
			formatting preferences for the JBoss DNA project.
		</para>
		<para>
			Then install Eclipse plugins for SVN and Maven.  (Remember, you will have to restart Eclipse after installing them.)
			We use the following plugins:
		</para>
		<table frame='all'>
			<title>Eclipse Subversion Plugins</title>
			<tgroup cols='2' align='left' colsep='1' rowsep='1'>
	      <colspec colname='c1' colwidth="1*"/>
	      <colspec colname='c2' colwidth="1*"/>
				<thead>
					<row>
			  		<entry>Eclipse Plugins</entry>
						<entry>Update Site URLs</entry>
					</row>
				</thead>
				<tbody>
					<row>
						<entry>Subversive SVN Client</entry>
						<entry>
							<ulink url="http://www.polarion.org/projects/subversive/download/eclipse/2.0/update-site/">http://www.polarion.org/projects/subversive/download/eclipse/2.0/update-site/</ulink>
						  <ulink url="http://www.polarion.org/projects/subversive/download/integrations/update-site/">http://www.polarion.org/projects/subversive/download/integrations/update-site/</ulink>
						</entry>
					</row>
					<row>
						<entry>Maven Integration for Eclipse</entry>
						<entry><ulink url="http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/update/">http://m2eclipse.sonatype.org/update/</ulink></entry>
					</row>
				</tbody>
			</tgroup>
		</table>
		<para>
			After you check out the JBoss DNA codebase, you can import the JBoss DNA Maven projects into Eclipse as Eclipse projects.
			To do this, go to "File->Import->Existing Projects", navigate to the <code>trunk/</code> folder in the import wizard,
			and then check each of the <link linkend="modules">subprojects</link> that you want to have in your workspace.
			Don't forget about the projects under <code>extensions/</code> or <code>docs/</code>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	<sect1 id="releasing">
		<title>Releasing</title>
		<para>
			This section outlines the basic process of releasing JBoss DNA.  This <emphasis role="strong">must</emphasis> be done
			either by the project lead or only after communicating with the project lead.
		</para>
		<para>
			Before continuing, your local workspace should contain no changes and should be a perfect reflection of Subversion.
			You can verify this by getting the latest from Subversion
		</para>
		<programlisting>$ svn update</programlisting> 
		<para>
			and ensuring that you have no additional changes with
		</para>
		<programlisting>$ svn status</programlisting>
		<para>
			You may also want to note the revision number for use later on in the process.  The release number is returned by
			the <code>svn update</code> command, but may also be found using
		</para>
		<programlisting>$ svn info</programlisting>
		<para>
			At this point, you're ready to verify that everything builds normally.
		</para>
		<sect2 id="build-all-artifacts-and-assemblies">
			<title>Building all artifacts and assemblies</title>
			<para>
				By default, the project's Maven build process does <emphasis>not</emphasis> build the documentation, JavaDocs, or assemblies.
				These take extra time, and most of our builds don't require them.  So the first step of releasing JBoss DNA
				is to use Maven to build all of regular artifacts (e.g., JARs) and these extra documents and assemblies.
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
					Before running Maven commands to build the releases, increase the memory available to Maven with this command:
					<code>$ export MAVEN_OPTS=-Xmx512m</code>
				</para>
			</note>
			<para>
				To perform this complete build, issue the following command while in the <code>trunk/</code> directory:
			</para>
			<programlisting>$ mvn -P assembly clean install</programlisting>
			<para>
				This command runs the "clean" and "install" goals using the "assembly" profile, 
				which adds the production of JavaDocs, the Getting Started document, the Reference Guide document, 
				the Getting Started examples, integration tests, and several ZIP archives.  The order of the goals is important.
			</para>
			<para>
				After this build has completed, verify that the assemblies under <code>target/</code> have actually been created and that
				they contain the correct information.
				At this point, we know that the actual Maven build process is building
				everything we want and will complete without errors.  We can now proceed with preparing for the release.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="determine-version">
			<title>Determine the version to be released</title>
			<para>
				The version being released should match the <ulink url="&JIRA;">JIRA</ulink> road map. Make sure that all issues related to the release are closed. 
				The project lead should be notified and approve that the release is taking place.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="release-dry-run">
			<title>Release dry run</title>
			<para>
				The next step is to ensure that all information in the POM is correct and contains all the information required for
				the release process.  This is called a <emphasis>dry run</emphasis>, and is done with the Maven "release" plugin:
			</para>
			<programlisting>$ mvn -P assembly release:prepare -DdryRun=true</programlisting>
			<para>
				This may download a lot of Maven plugins if they already haven't been downloaded, but it will eventually prompt you for
				the release version of each of the Maven projects, the tag name for the release, and the next development versions
				(again for each of the Maven projects).  The default values are probably acceptable; if not, then check that the 
				"<code>&lt;version&gt;</code>" tags in each of the POM files is correct and end with "-SNAPSHOT".
			</para>
			<para>
				After the dry run completes you should clean up the files that the release plugin created in the dry run:
			</para>
			<programlisting>$ mvn -P assembly release:clean</programlisting>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="prepare-release">
			<title>Prepare for the release</title>
			<para>
				Run the prepare step (without the <code>dryRun</code> option):
			</para>
			<programlisting>$ mvn -P assembly release:prepare</programlisting>
			<para>
				You will again be prompted for the release versions and tag name. These should be the same as what was used during the dry run. 
				This will run the same steps as the dry run, with the additional step of tagging the release in SVN.  
			</para>
			<para>
				If there are any problems during this step, you should go back and try the dry run option.  But after this runs successfully,
				the release will be tagged in SVN, and the <code>pom.xml</code> files in SVN under <code>/trunk</code> will have the 
				next version in the "&lt;version&gt;" values.
				However, the artifacts for the release are not yet published.  That's the next step.
			</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2 id="release">
			<title>Perform the release</title>
			<para>
				At this point, the release's artifacts need to be published to the JBoss Maven repository.  This next command check outs the
				files from the release tag created earlier (into a <code>trunk/target/checkout</code> directory), runs a build, and then
				deploys the generated artifacts.  Note that this ensures that the artifacts are built from the tagged code.
			</para>
			<programlisting>$ mvn release:perform -DuseReleaseProfile=false</programlisting>
			<note>
				<para>
					If during this process you get an error finding the released artifacts in your local Maven repository, you may 
					need to go into the <code>trunk/target/checkout</code> folder and run <code>$ mvn install</code>.  This is a simple
					workaround to make the artifacts available locally.  Another option to try is adding <code>-Dgoals=install,assembly</code> 
					to the <code>$ mvn release:perform... </code> command above.
				</para>
			</note>
			<para>
				The release has been performed, but we still need to build and deploy the <emphasis>real</emphasis> artifacts
				to the JBoss Maven repository.  To do
				this, go to a working area and check out the recently-produced SVN tag (using the correct <code>{release-number}</code>):
			</para>
			<programlisting>$ svn checkout https://anonsvn.jboss.org/repos/dna/tags/dna-{release-number}/</programlisting>
			<para>
				Then, go into the new directory, and perform a Maven deploy:
			</para>
			<programlisting>$ mvn clean deploy</programlisting>
			<para>
				This will rebuild all the artifacts (from your local copy of the <emphasis>tagged</emphasis> source) and deploy them
				to the local file system, which is comprised of a local checkout of the JBoss Maven2 repository 
				in a location specified by a combination of the <code>&lt;distributionManagement&gt;</code> section of several <code>pom.xml</code> 
				files and your personal <code>settings.xml</code> file.  Once this Maven command completes, you will need to 
				commit the new files after they are deployed.  For more information, see the 
				<ulink url="http://wiki.jboss.org/wiki/Maven">JBoss wiki</ulink>.
			</para>
			<para>
				At this point, the software has been released and tagged, and it's been deployed to a local checked-out copy of the 
				JBoss DNA Maven 2 repository (via the "&lt;distribution&gt;" section of the pom.xml files).  Those need to be committed
				into the Maven 2 repository using SVN.  And finally, the last thing is to publish the release onto
				the project's <ulink url="&Downloads;">downloads</ulink> and <ulink url="&Home;/docs">documentation</ulink> pages.
			</para>
			<para>
				The assemblies of the source, binaries, etc. also need to be published onto the &Downloads; area of the
				<ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/dna">the project page</ulink>.  This process is expected to change, as <ulink url="http://www.jboss.org">JBoss.org</ulink>
				improves its infrastructure.
			</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
	<sect1>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<para>
			In this chapter, we described the various aspects of developing code for the JBoss DNA project.  
			Next, we must discuss the testing practices for JBoss DNA project.
		  This is the topic of the <link linkend="testing">next chapter</link>.
		</para>
	</sect1>
</chapter>
