<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
      "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="downloading">
  <title>Downloading the examples</title>
  <para>JBoss DNA is built using Maven 2, so it's much easier to following along with the examples in this document
    if you install and configure Maven.  Once this is done, you can very easily build the examples or even create a maven project that
    depends on the JBoss DNA JARs.  Maven will automatically download the right versions of the JARs, including those other libraries
    on which JBoss DNA depends.  Maven also makes it very easy to create an assembly of your final application
    so that you can package into a distributable form.</para>
  <para>
    The examples created for this User Guide use Maven2 to achieve exactly this so it is highly recommended that you
    <ulink url="http://labs.jboss.com/file-access/default/members/jbossmc/downloads/userGuide-examples-13112007.zip">download</ulink>
    these first and take a look at how they work.
  </para>
  <note>
    <para>
      To build and run the examples you first need to install and configure Maven 2.0.7 available from
      <ulink url="http://maven.apache.org/">http://maven.apache.org/</ulink>
    </para>
    <para>Installation is performed by downloading and unzipping the maven-2.0.7-bin.zip file to a convenient location
      on your local disk. Configuration consists of adding $MAVEN_HOME/bin to your path and adding the following profile to your
      ~/.m2/settings.xml file:</para>
    <programlisting role="XML">&lt;settings&gt;
  &lt;profiles&gt;
    &lt;profile&gt;
      &lt;id&gt;jboss.repository&lt;/id&gt;
      &lt;activation&gt;
        &lt;property&gt;          
          &lt;name&gt;!jboss.repository.off&lt;/name&gt;
        &lt;/property&gt;
      &lt;/activation&gt;
      &lt;repositories&gt;
        &lt;repository&gt;
          &lt;id&gt;snapshots.jboss.org&lt;/id&gt;
          &lt;url&gt;http://snapshots.jboss.org/maven2&lt;/url&gt;
          &lt;snapshots&gt;
            &lt;enabled&gt;true&lt;/enabled&gt;
          &lt;/snapshots&gt;
        &lt;/repository&gt;
        &lt;repository&gt;
          &lt;id&gt;repository.jboss.org&lt;/id&gt;
          &lt;url&gt;http://repository.jboss.org/maven2&lt;/url&gt;
          &lt;snapshots&gt;
            &lt;enabled&gt;false&lt;/enabled&gt;
          &lt;/snapshots&gt;
        &lt;/repository&gt;
      &lt;/repositories&gt;
      &lt;pluginRepositories&gt;
        &lt;pluginRepository&gt;
          &lt;id&gt;repository.jboss.org&lt;/id&gt;
          &lt;url&gt;http://repository.jboss.org/maven2&lt;/url&gt;
          &lt;snapshots&gt;
            &lt;enabled&gt;false&lt;/enabled&gt;
          &lt;/snapshots&gt;
        &lt;/pluginRepository&gt;
        &lt;pluginRepository&gt;
          &lt;id&gt;snapshots.jboss.org&lt;/id&gt;
          &lt;url&gt;http://snapshots.jboss.org/maven2&lt;/url&gt;
          &lt;snapshots&gt;
            &lt;enabled&gt;true&lt;/enabled&gt;
          &lt;/snapshots&gt;
        &lt;/pluginRepository&gt;
      &lt;/pluginRepositories&gt;
    &lt;/profile&gt;
  &lt;/profiles&gt;
&lt;/settings&gt;</programlisting>
        <para>This profile informs maven of the two JBoss repositories (snapshots and releases) that are needed to download the JBoss Microcontainer and dependant JARs.</para>
      </note>
      <para>Once you have configured Maven and downloaded the examples then you can go to one of the following subdirectories in the <code>examples/User_Guide</code> directory and enter <code>mvn install</code> to perform a build:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>gettingStarted -  projects for creating and using a service together with AOP</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>pojoDevelopment -  examples of creating and configuring POJOs using XML and annotations</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>aopDevelopment - examples of using AOP to add behaviour to POJOs</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>extending - examples of how we  created various extensions to the microcontainer by creating new dependencies</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>Instructions on how to run the individual examples can be found in the corresponding parts of this guide.</para>
</chapter>